<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sanctuary for honest men. Or An abstract of humane wisedome Contayning, a certaine way leading to a perfect knowledge of Man, and directing to a discreet cariage in the vvhole course of our humane condition. Collected and composed by Io: Hitchcock student in the Middle Temple.</title>
            <author>Hitchcock, John, student in the Middle Temple.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118697</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853904</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853904</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 579:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sanctuary for honest men. Or An abstract of humane wisedome Contayning, a certaine way leading to a perfect knowledge of Man, and directing to a discreet cariage in the vvhole course of our humane condition. Collected and composed by Io: Hitchcock student in the Middle Temple.</title>
                  <author>Hitchcock, John, student in the Middle Temple.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 181, [11] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin for Thomas Norton at the signe of the Kings head in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A moral discourse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The abstract of humane wisdome.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19305:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19305:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SANCTVARY FOR HONEST MEN.</p>
            <p>OR <hi>An Abſtract of Humane</hi> WISDOME.</p>
            <p>Contayning, A certaine way leading to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowledge of MAN, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting to a diſcreet Cariage in the whole courſe of our <hi>Humane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ondition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected and compoſed By Io: HITCHCOCK Student in <hi>the Middle Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Virtus eſt vitium fugere, &amp; ſapientia ſcire</l>
               <l>Quid veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> decens, quid fas, quid &amp; vule, quid non.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin</hi> for <hi>Thomas Nort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> at the ſigne of the Kings head in Paules Churchyard. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19305:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19305:2"/>
            <head>TO THE right Honourable WILLIAM Earle of PEMBROKE, <hi>Lord</hi> HERBERT of <hi>Cardiffe, Marmion,</hi> and <hi>S. Quintin,</hi> Lord CHAMBERLAINE to his MAIESTIE, Knight of the moſt Noble Order of <hi>the</hi> GARTER, <hi>one of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt Honorable Priuy</hi> COVNCELL.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo things <hi>(right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable)</hi> are vſually the Apologicall ſubiects
<pb facs="tcp:19305:3"/> of moſt dedications, the worthineſſe of the Patron, and the ſelfe-diſtruſting inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the one concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth mee, the other your HONORABLE SELFE, whom each generous Spirit hath ſo iuſtly made the aemulated patterne of true Nobility and Virtue that I could not eaſily containe my ſelfe, but was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly conſtrayned with an affectionate deſire to dedicate this ſmall mite of my
<pb facs="tcp:19305:3"/> poore endeauours, this handfull of Morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vnto you, though no deſert in my ſelfe can euer bee worthy inough to make mee knowne to your HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOUR, nor any thing ſo well handled in this conciſe volume, but may either bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled by your riper iudgment, or elſe be corrected by the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of your life: yet (aſſuring my ſelfe that your generous and truly ennobled minde will willingly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whatſoeuer is
<pb facs="tcp:19305:4"/> well intended) I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſhelter this little compendious Tract vnder your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable patronage, <hi>ſic non Zoilum metuo, non inuidiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all ſincerity of duty moſt humbly affectionate, <hi>Io: Hitchcock.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19305:4"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>IT was not my purpoſe (captious or indifferent Reader) to ſend this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Antidote into the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry iawes of the world which was prepared onely for my owne dyet, but the preuayling importunitie of freinds (which commonly ſerueth others for excuſe) was to me a neceſſity: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince this diſh is now come to be ſerued to thy Table, and ſo to be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by thy well or ill di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing pallate (I meane thy raſh or ſounder iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) let me aduiſe thee, if thou mean'ſt to be nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by it, firſt to ruminate
<pb facs="tcp:19305:5"/> and chew it well, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to concoct it through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before thou reiect it as an excrement; and then if any thing herein reliſh thee feede heartily, and welcom; but if this diſtaſte thee, either leaue it friendly, or diſh out thy owne. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere vel noli noſtra, vel ede tua.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19305:5"/>
            <head>The Abſtract OF <hi>Humane Wiſdome.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt part of this Booke teaching the knowledge of our ſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ISDOME,<note place="margin">Wiſdom in generall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed</note> (howſoeuer wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it) is a ſingular and more than ordinary qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or habit of the mind. And the word is diuerſly taken; firſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgarely,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19305:6"/> (though ſometimes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly) for an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meaſure of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency in whatſoeuer, be it good or euill. And in this ſenſe a man may be ſaid to bee wiſe as well in thoſe things that are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; diuelliſh, as thoſe that are honeſt and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable.</p>
               <p>Secondly it is taken <hi>Morally</hi> (&amp; indeed more properly) for a diſcreete gouernment of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire man in things that are good, honeſt, and profitable.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is taken <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologically,</hi> for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of heauenly things, or for a ſupernaturall gift of grace infuſed by the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19305:6"/> Spirit of GOD.</p>
               <p>So that from hence wee may eaſily perceiue three ſorts of Wiſdome, Diuine, Humane, and Mundane, correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to GOD, Nature pure and entire, Nature vitiated and corrupted.</p>
               <p>But (to omit the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which is Diuine &amp; Metaphyſicall, as alſo that which is Mundane and worldly; the one as too high and aboue the ſphaere of Morality; the other as too baſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to fil vp the room in this little Treatiſe) the only ſubiect of this Tract is that which is Humane, and teacheth the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and gouernment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19305:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> of our ſelues as wee are men in our humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Humane wiſdome deſcribed. <hi>1.</hi> negatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note>And it is not (as ſome ſuppoſe) an ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſed cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and diſcretion in our affaires &amp; conuerſation, for this is onely outward and in action, and may be without eſſentiall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty or piety: nor (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to others) a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, ſtrict and Stoicall auſterity in opinions, words, manners, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of life; for this is rather extrauagancy and madneſſe:<note place="margin">2. <hi>poſitiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
                  </note> But (in a word) it is a ſweet and regular managing of the ſoule by the law of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; or an exact and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable rule by which a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19305:7"/> man is able to direct and guide his thoughts, words, and actions with integrity, decency, and order.</p>
               <p>And it may be attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by two meanes;<note place="margin">How it is attained.</note> the firſt is Naturall, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the good tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſeede of the Parents, the milke of the Nurſe, and the firſt edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. The ſecond is acquired by induſtry and the ſtudy of good books, and conferring with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, iudicious, and wiſe men.</p>
               <p>NOw this Humane wiſdome (which is the ſubiect of this tract,<note place="margin">The diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</note> and the excellency of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19305:8"/> man as he is man) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth two parts; the firſt is <hi>Theorike,</hi> ſhewing the knowledge of our ſelues, both of the inward and outward man: the ſecond <hi>Practike,</hi> for the well ordering of our ſelues after this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, by following or flying that which is good or euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Man two waies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</note>For the better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſelues wee may conſider man two waies; firſt <hi>Naturally,</hi> by the compoſition of his partes, by his difference from other creatures, and by his life. Secondly <hi>Morally,</hi> by his humours and conditions, and by the difference of one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19305:8"/> man from an other.</p>
               <p>IN the conſideration of man by the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his parts it is eaſie to vnderſtand that euery man is compoſed of a body and a ſoule;<note place="margin">The first naturall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſary and in ſome ſort conducible to wiſdome to haue (at the leaſt) a generall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our bodies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the inclinations of the minde (according to philoſophy) moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly follow the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the body.</p>
               <p>But (not to ſtand vpon the long connexion of the inward and outward parts of the body, being more pertinent to Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke and Anatomy then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19305:9"/> this preſent diſcourſe) the braine is the chiefeſt part that makes for our purpoſe, and moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be knowne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe from hence procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the whole wracke or welfare of a man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the good or ill temperature thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The braine.</note>For this ſoueraigne part nature hath careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouided as the quein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt peece of her work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip; and therefore it is curiouſly incloſed within two skinnes, the one <hi>dura mater,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hard and thicke; the other <hi>pia mater,</hi> very thinne and ſoft; within which is the braine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of an oily matter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19305:9"/> delicate &amp; ſubtle, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if the heate and cold, dryth and moiſture bee well and proportionably mixt, that man is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably temperd, and (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to nature) hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily borne, ſtrong, heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, wiſe, and iudicious: therefore as ſoone as the body becomes organi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, the ſoule makes choice of this part for her cheifeſt manſion, where ſhe may beſt exerciſe her faculties, which are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially three, a <hi>vegetatiue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The facul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties of the ſoule.</note> 
                  <hi>ſenſitiue, &amp; intellectiue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>egetatiue</hi> hath a threefold virtue,<note place="margin">The vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty.</note> 
                  <hi>Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iue</hi> for the attraction, concoction, &amp; digeſtion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19305:10"/> of the victuals, retayning the good and expelling the ſuperfluous: <hi>Exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue</hi> for the proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enlarging and exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of all the parts of the body; and <hi>Generatiue</hi> for the conſeruation of the kinde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue.</note>The <hi>Senſitiue</hi> (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the number of the ſenſes) hath a fiuefold virtue, whereby euery ſenſe by his organ and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument diſtinguiſheth and iudgeth of his owne proper obiect, as the ſight of colours, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſounds, the ſmell of odours, the taſte of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, the touch of wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer is tangible.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the intellectiue of humane ſoule.</note>The <hi>Intellectiue</hi> (which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19305:10"/> is onely proper to man) hath three principall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties ſeated in three cloſets of the braine, where (according to the moſt embraced opinion) they exerciſe their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions not diſtinctly and apart, but in common all three together; the <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination</hi> ſeruing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and apprehend the images of things; the <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> to examine &amp; try by the touchſtone of reaſon the verity &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lity of the thing concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; the <hi>Memory</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and keepe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer wee heare, ſee, or read.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Imagination</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly<note place="margin">The imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> ſtrongeſt in young
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19305:11"/> men, by reaſon of the feruent heat of the braine wherby the humours are rarified and purified; the <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> ripeſt in old men,<note place="margin">Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> which commonly excell in maturity of iudgement by reaſon of the drynes of the braine;<note place="margin">Memory.</note> the <hi>Memory</hi> is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue in children, by reaſon of the abundance of moiſture and oily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance fit for impreſſion and retention.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The order and cauſes of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note>Now from theſe facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoule proceed all the ſtormy tempeſts or quiet calmes in the whole life of man; either wee ſaile ſecurely by the iudiciall ſterne of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, or elſe wee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19305:11"/> are caried headlong into the turbulent ſea of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the furious windes of our raſh imagination and inconſiderate will. For when the imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is corrupted, either by the miſſe conceit of the ſenſes that conceiue not things aright as they are but as they ſeeme to bee, or by a preſumptuous and preiudicate opinion grounded vpon the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous report of the vulgar, the will is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſt with a raſh reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and begins to act and put in practiſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the imagination vpon the information of the ſenſes hath conceiued to be good or euill; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19305:12"/> ſo (either not taking counſell of the iudgment and vnderſtanding at all, or elſe deceiuing it with a ſuperficiall apparance of good or euill) it beginnes preſently to moue the power concupiſcible and iraſcible, cauſing vs to loue, hate, feare, hope, deſpaire, and the like; ſo that all our paſſions ariſe immediately from the will, being moued with an outward apparance and opinion of good or euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The will.</note>Now the will is ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and dulled by diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty and faſcility, rarity and abundance, abſence and preſent fruition: and when it is moued with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19305:12"/> the ſemblance of good,<note place="margin">The diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note> this paſſion is <hi>Loue;</hi> and if it be preſent, it is <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> and <hi>Ioy;</hi> if to come <hi>Deſire,</hi> and ſtirreth vp in our hearts <hi>Hope</hi> &amp; <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire:</hi> but if the will be moued by the ſemblance of euill, this paſſion is <hi>Hate;</hi> and if it be preſent in our ſelues it is <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Greife,</hi> in others <hi>Pitty</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion;</hi> and if it be to come it is <hi>Feare,</hi> &amp; &amp; ſtirreth vp in our hearts <hi>Choler, Enuy, Iealouſie, Reuenge, Cruelty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>LOue</hi> (which is the firſt &amp; moſt naturall paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) is either the loue of greatneſſe and honour,<note place="margin">Loue in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided.</note> which is <hi>Ambition;</hi> or of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19305:13"/> riches, which is <hi>Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> or of carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which is <hi>Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ambition.</note>
                  <hi>Ambition</hi> is a thirſty &amp; gluttonous deſire of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and preferment, yet naturall by reaſon of the inſatiability of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is <hi>imperiſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per auida, alwaies greedy of authority,</hi> and it is moſt commonly lodged in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous ſpirits that are au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious to vndertake high and difficult at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note>
                  <hi>Couetouſneſſe</hi> is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate care of heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp riches, not reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the honeſty or lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dableneſſe of the meanes whereby they are gotten;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19305:13"/> for <hi>lucri bonus est odor ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e qualibet, the ſent of gaine is ſweet though it come from a Iakes.</hi> This paſſion is commonly inthroned in vulgar &amp; degenerous mindes, that feare pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as a ſerpent, and adore riches as a God; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they make haſte by all poſſible meanes to be wealthy, by extortion, vſury, bribery, and what not? rather ſeruing their riches than enioying them, and are alwaies poore in heaps of gold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Carnall Loue</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence</hi> is terminated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the mutuall pleaſure of both Sexes,<note place="margin">Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.</note> a thing naturall and indifferent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n all, and neither in it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19305:14"/> ſelfe nor in the action vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious nor ignominious, but in the vnchaſte and immoderate vſe thereof, and the bad meanes of obteyning it: <hi>ſic mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> magis quam re ipsâ labora mus, the way to attaine i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> doth more trouble vs the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the thing it ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Paſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from an appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring good.</note>And theſe are the thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> branches of the tree o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Loue,</hi> which are formed vpon the obiect of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appearing good: Now if we haue the thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in our preſent poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſion wee are wonder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully glad and reioyce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and then this paſſion i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> called <hi>Ioy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joy.</note> which is an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſiue pleaſure ariſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the delight we tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19305:14"/> in the thing obteyned, making vs commonly merry and iocund: But if it be not in our preſent poſſeſſion (being a thing in our conceipt ſimply good) we endeuour by all meanes poſſible to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheiue it; this is <hi>Deſire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deſire.</note> which is an eager care to obteine the thing that ſeemeth good vnto vs, making vs commonly diligent and painefull in the purſuit thereof; ſo that if we ſee any likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of obteyning the thing deſired, wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort on our ſelues with a continuall expectation of the fruition thereof; and this is <hi>Hope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hope.</note> which is nothing but a credulous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19305:15"/> aſſurance of enioying our deſire: But if we ſee no probabilitie of getting that which we ſeeke for, wee begin preſently to droope in our affections, and deſiſt to ſeeke any farther meanes for the obteyning thereof; and this is <hi>Deſpaire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſpaire.</note> which is a diſtruſtfull opinion grounded vpon the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of obteyning our deſire.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Paſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from an appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring euill eſtate.</note>But contrarily when any thing preſents it ſelfe vnto vs which ſeemeth or appeareth to be euill, wee preſently loath and contemne it; and then this paſſion is called <hi>Hate,</hi> which is a diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conceipt of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19305:15"/> euill; ſo that when vpon the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of it we conceiue it to be euill (and therfore hate it) we happily ſtand in doubt that it may ſometime come vpon vs; this is <hi>Feare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Feare.</note> which is a timorous apprehenſion of an euill to come, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vs to endeuour to ſhun and auoide it; and if wee finde this euill in our ſelues which wee ſo much hate and feare, we are much perplexed and afflicted; and this is <hi>Greife,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Griefe.</note> which is a deepe impreſſion of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the euill that tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vs, vpon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt whereof the heart is preſently ſurprized and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19305:16"/> deiected, and the ſpirit dulled and infeebled, ſo that we can doe nothing for the preſent but blub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our faces, hang downe our heads, and fixe our eyes vpon the ground: ſometimes it is more violent, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaueth vs of the vſe of diſcourſe, reaſon, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and quite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſheth the faculties of the ſoule, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times life it ſelfe. But when we ſee any euill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall an other wee are not ſo violently afflicted, but are moued with a kinde of paſſionate remorſe, &amp; this is called <hi>Pitty:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pitty.</note> which is an effeminate fellow-feeling of the euills that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19305:16"/> befall an other.</p>
               <p>THE other bitter ſtreames of this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled fountaine of <hi>Hate</hi> are theſe, <hi>Choler, Enuy, Iealouſie, Reuenge, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Choler</hi> is a furious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the minde,<note place="margin">Choler.</note> ariſing ſometimes from lightnes in beleeuing, a tender niceneſſe of nature, ouer-preciſe curioſity, or a loue of trifles; but moſt commonly from an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of contempt or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe either in word, deed or countenance. This paſſion is moſt incident to children, ſicke perſons, and old folkes by reaſon of the weakneſſe of their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19305:17"/> ſpirit, for <hi>invalidum omne naturâ querulum eſt, euery thing that is weake is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to diſquiet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Enuy.</note>
                  <hi>Enuy</hi> is an effect of <hi>Hate,</hi> cauſing vs to thinke euery thing too much or too good, that an other whom we hate, doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy; <hi>hinc vicinum pecus grandius vber habet,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>This Enuy hath, that all in whom it's bred</l>
                     <l>Still thinke their neighbors oxe is better fed.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iealouſie.</note>
                  <hi>Iealouſie</hi> is a doubting opinion or a miſtruſtfull conceipt that an other enioyeth that which wee feare or deſire, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee alwaies lay in gariſon with a continuall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19305:17"/> and euer-watchfull care to finde and preuent it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reuenge</hi> is a thirſty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of ſatisfaction for a wrong done to a mans perſon or reputation in word or deede,<note place="margin">Reuenge.</note> ariſing commonly from <hi>greife</hi> or <hi>choler</hi> by a conceipt of the greatnes of the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that is offer'd: for ſo tender we are of a wrong, that we eſteeme reuenge ſweeter then life it ſelfe, and therefore wee ſeeke it amidſt a thouſand dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cruelty</hi> is a thing baſe &amp; inhumane,<note place="margin">Cruelty.</note> and therefore by the Latines fitly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>feritas,</hi> becauſe it makes vs forget all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane mercy &amp; compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19305:18"/> and taketh delight in bloud and murder, not reſpecting the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or vnworthineſſe of the enemie, nor the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond naturall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man.</note>IN the ſecond naturall conſideration of man (which is by his diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) wee may note his worthines and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; firſt becauſe man is the image of GOD, formed vpright, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies looking vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as the onely place and hauen of his reſt and happineſſe: Secondly becauſe hee is the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and quinteſſenſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nature, being all naked,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19305:18"/> and (by reaſon of the thinne and delicate tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the humours) moſt beautifull; which beautie is inthroned eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the face or viſage, the incendiary of loue, the ſeate of laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and kiſſing, and the looking-glaſſe of the ſoule, becauſe it is ap to declare our inward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and paſſions, as ioy when we looke cheerful, greife and anger when we looke dull and frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſhame when wee bluſh, feare when wee waxe pale, and the like. Thirdly wee may ſee the excellence of man by the praerogatiue ſupremacy that God hath giuen him
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19305:19"/> ouer the fowles of the aire, the fiſh of the ſea, and the beaſts of the field; wherefore he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with reaſon, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and iudgement to gouerne both himſelfe and them: So that man being a demi-God aboue other creatures, it ſhould be a ſhame for him to be taught by them to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate his appetite and pleaſure in eating, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and carnall copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for euen in theſe &amp; many other things the very beaſts excell vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third naturall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man.</note>IN the third naturall conſideration of man (which is by his life) we ſhould take notice firſt of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19305:19"/> the ſhortneſſe thereof, being in the courſe of nature but thirty or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y yeeres at the moſt by reaſon of the halfe that is ſpent in ſleepe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly of the vices wee are naturally prone vnto; in our youth vnto teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, vnbridled liberty, and an vnſatiable deſire of pleaſure naturally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the ſtrong and vigorous heate of the bloud; and in olde age to proteruitie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from infirmity, ſuperſtition from curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, a conceite of much knowledge from long experience, a ſottiſh aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice from the feare of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, a contempt or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19305:20"/> feare of death from the loue of the world. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince theſe vices are naturally incident vnto vs, we ſhould ſtudy to preuent them before they come vpon vs, and take care to ſpend our life well, becauſe it is ſhort, becauſe it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The morall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O attaine yet to a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowledg of our ſelues wee muſt conſider man <hi>morally,</hi> firſt by his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and conditions, ſecondly by the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of one man from an other.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19305:20"/>
               <p>In the conſideration of man by his humours and conditions wee may note his <hi>vanity, weaknes, inconſtancy, miſerie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vanity of man we may ſee firſt imaginarily in his thoughts;<note place="margin">Vanity.</note> one plotteth how hee may make himſelfe famous, an other how hee would liue if hee were a great man, an other what kind of geſture doth beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him, another mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth how men will ſpeake of him when he is dead, with what pompe they will celebrate his obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, and the like. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly wee may ſee the vanity of man really in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19305:21"/> his actions if wee marke how ſome torment and vex themſelues in triuiall matters that are vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of their care, how vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent they are for the ill flying of a hawke, the running of a dogge, or if they be any way croſt in their ſports; or if wee conſider what an age of time ſome men conſume in learning to ſing, to daunce, to manage a horſe, and the like, neuer ſeeking that which is ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and more neceſſary how to liue well and commodiouſly, but like <hi>Aeſops</hi> dogge omitting the ſubſtanc for a ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. Thirdly wee may ſee the vanity of man in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19305:21"/> the tickling pleaſure and felicitie that ſome men take in things collaterall and impertinent, that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n themſelues neither vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious nor much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable; as ſome, if they can but comple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment with a grace, ſpeak mouingly, and court their Miſtreſſe with a plauſible facility, O they are men aboue the Moone, and as proud as <hi>Alexanders</hi> horſe of his golden trappings.</p>
               <p>The weakneſſe or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becility of man wee may perceiue firſt in our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,<note place="margin">Weakneſſe.</note> either not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deſire and chuſe that which is beſt, or diſliking that wee haue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19305:22"/> choſen; Secondly in the vſe of things, being not able to make the beſt of them, becauſe wee know not their true and ſimple nature; Thirdly in our beſt actions, <hi>quod non bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num benè facimus, in that we doe not the good we doe after a good manner;</hi> Fourthly in the nice kind of life that ſome men addict themſelues vnto; they mue vp themſelues at home, and neuer ſee the face of a publike aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, but liue as it were in a well or a bottle, and therefore are vnfit to be employed for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, becauſe they ſee nothing clerely, but a far off and through
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19305:22"/> a hole, and vnderſtand onely by tradition and report. Fiftly in the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſabling faſhion of moſt men that enthrall their iudgement and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding vnder the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of authoritie, and approue of nothing without <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> &amp; <hi>Plato</hi> or an <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> for their opinion.</p>
               <p>The Inconſtancie of man we may eaſily ſee if wee note how wauering we are in all our actions,<note place="margin">Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> wee deſire what we reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and reiect what we lately deſired; we chuſe, &amp; we diſlike our choice; wee loue, and preſently we hate what we loued, euery houre wee change
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19305:23"/> our decree; ſo that in this reſpect man may well be ſaid to be <hi>prorſus aliud à ſe ipſo, quite different or an other thing from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Miſery.</note>The miſerie of man wee may note firſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, in our ſhamefull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into the world, the feebleneſſe of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, the infinite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of diſeaſes wee are ſubiect to in our youth, eſpecially hotte and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning maladies, by reaſon of the infla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mation of the bloud; and deliration and dottage in our olde age, by reaſon of the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment of the ſpirits; Secondly inwardly, in the imagination that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19305:23"/> with continuall expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion praeoccupateth euils <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o come; in the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that is dull and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncapable of high and weighty affaires, &amp; blind in diſcerning the veritie of opinions; in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory that continually retaineth the euills that annoy vs; in the will that is headlong and raſh to execute any thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pondering whether it be good or euill.</p>
               <p>The preſumption or arrogancy of man wee may note firſt in reſpect of other creatures,<note place="margin">Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> in that we vilifie and debaſe them too much as if they were not the workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; Secondly in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19305:24"/> reſpect of man our aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate and companion, in that we ſcorne to learne one of another, euery man thinkes hee can ſee farre into a milſtone, and therefore we perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beleiue or misbeleiue that which at the firſt ſight ſeemeth true or falſe vnto vs, whereupon we preſently beginne to condemne or approue whatſoeuer wee haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued or misbeleeued, and go about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade others either to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it as a maxime, or reiect it as abſurd. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in reſpect of God and Nature, in that in the proſperous ſucceſſe of our worldly affaires wee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19305:24"/> attribute nothing wholly to the free gift and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, but to our owne endeauours and worthineſſe, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of Nature; wee thinke the Sunne muſt needes ſhine, the raine fall, and the earth of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie yeeld her increaſe onely for vs; So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though man in his whole life be nothing but a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell of vanitie, weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, inconſtancy, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and a world of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, yet hee is moſt proudly preſumptuous, and preſumptuouſlie proud, like a beggar that glories in his ſtinking ragges, &amp; lyce that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually annoy him.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:19305:25"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond morall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of man.</note>SEcondly (to know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our humane eſtate the better) we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider man by the diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence of one man from an other.<note place="margin">Difference of men in reſpect of the climate</note> Firſt in reſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the climate wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they liue which is power<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full both in the outwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> complexion, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward nature and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; Some men are in colour ſanguine and phlegmatike, of body ſtrong, of ſtature bigge and tall, but weake in minde, blockiſh and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, as commonly thoſe in the Northerne parts of the world, by reaſon of the inward naturall heate which in them is moſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19305:25"/> feruent becauſe the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the circumſtant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aire incloſeth the heate and driues it to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth theſe effects; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily others are blacke &amp; melancholike, leſſe of ſtature, but more inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and wiſe, as thoſe in the Southerne &amp; hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter parts of the world where the vigour of the externall heate doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxe and open the pores, and diſſipate and exhale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he inward heate, and cauſeth the diuerſitie. Therfore as <hi>Plato</hi> thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d God that he was an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>henian</hi> and not a <hi>Theban,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecauſe the aire was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here more thinne and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19305:26"/> delicat, and therefore the men more dexterious and witty, ſo wee haue great cauſe to praiſe him, firſt that hee hath made vs Chriſtians and not Infidells. Secondly that he hath plac'd vs in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in a temperate cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and fertile ſoyle, where we haue all things in plenty and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Difference of men in reſpect of capacity &amp; vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note>Secondly we may ſee the difference of men in reſpect of their capacity and vnderſtanding, and ſo wee may note three ſorts of people in euery nation and common-wealth; the firſt are but the lees and dregs of the people, vulgar and abiect
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19305:26"/> ſpirits borne onely to ſerue and obey. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond are a kinde of men of an indifferent vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, but common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeduced by tradition, and the cuſtome of the place where they liue; the third are men of a quicke ſpirit and an acute iudgement, not beſotted with the common opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world, but of themſelues able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the verity and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of things.</p>
               <p>Thirdly we may note this difference in reſpect of ſuperiority and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority,<note place="margin">Difference of men in reſpect of ſuperiority and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority.</note> which is either publike or priuate; the publike is for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious gouernment of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19305:27"/> the State either immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate betweene the Prince himſelfe &amp; his ſubiects, or ſubordinate betweene the ſubiects and the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers that repreſent the perſon of the Prince, as perticular Lords, Iudges, Iuſtices, Mayors and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inferiour Officers; the Priuate is for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent managing of rurall and domeſticall affaires betweene the Husband and the Wife, Parents &amp; Children, Maſters and Seruants; and in theſe three caſes a man muſt obſerue this decorum, to vſe his wife neither as his Miſtreſſe nor his ſeruant, his ſeruant not as his ſlaue nor his fellow; his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19305:27"/> childe neither as his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, his fellow, nor his maſter.</p>
               <p>Fourthly wee may ſee the difference of one man from an other by the diuerſitie of their profeſſion and kinde of life:<note place="margin">Difference of men in reſpect of profeſſion and kinde of life.</note> Some men affect a ſolitary and retired life, to ſequeſter themſelues from company and the troubles both of dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall and publike af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires; others delight in a more ſociable life, to talke, to reaſon, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to make vſe of a Companion; others make choice of the countrey for the vicinity of the fields, the woods, the riuers, for hawking
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19305:28"/> hunting, fiſhing, fowling, and other ſports and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations: others ſhut vp themſelues in Citties and Townes, and ſpend their time in viſitation, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement and company keeping: others are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged with the ſound of the trumpet, the noiſe of the drumme and fife, and delight in ſtratagems and warlike diſcipline: others delight in trauell, to ſee the conditions of the men, the diuerſitie of their manners, the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Countrey, and the politick gouernment of the State; and briefly <hi>vt mens cuiuſque ſic eſt quiſque, Euery man as hee affects ſo hee liues,</hi> ſo that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19305:28"/> in euery man wee may note three kinds of liues, the firſt inward to a mans ſelfe in his thoughts and imaginations, the ſecond domeſticall in his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate affaires, the third publike to the view of the world.</p>
               <p>Laſtly we may ſee the difference of men by the diuerſity of the fauours and disfauours of nature and Fortune. 1.<note place="margin">Difference of men in reſpect of nature &amp; fortune.</note> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Nobilitie and Honour, which is either naturall by diſcent, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by deſert; Some by bloud are noble, ſome by their owne vertues, ſome by both, ſome by neither of theſe. 2. In reſpect of Science and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19305:29"/> knowledge both theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke and practicke, ſome are good in the one, ſome in the other, ſome in nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 3. In reſpect of riches and pouerty; ſome are endowed with great poſſeſſions, lands, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, and all the fauours of Fortune, others haue ſcarce a houſe to defend them from the iniurie of the raine and winde. 4. In reſpect of liberty, which is either internall of the minde, or externall of the body; as for the firſt, wee ſee ſome are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled by their paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, others cary them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues quietly in all things without diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; as for the ſecond,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19305:29"/> we ſee ſome men liue (as their fancie leades them) now in one place, now in another, and haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to expatiate the whole earth, while others are confined within the narrow walles of a darke and vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:19305:30"/>
               <head>The ſecond part of this Booke, conteyning the generall inſtructions of Wiſdome which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect all men alike.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow wee haue attayned by the naturall &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man to a breife knowledge of our ſelues (which is the firſt and Theorike part of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) it behooueth vs to make vſe of this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to order our ſelues wiſely and diſcreetly by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19305:30"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is the ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Practicke part of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome; for a man is not herefore honeſt or vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous, becauſe he knowes what is virtuous or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, but becauſe he doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he things that are ſo; <hi>Virtutis omnis in hoc laus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>est, the praiſe of virtue conſists in the action.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler ordering of our ſelues according to WISDOME there are rules and praeſcriptions both generall for all men alike, and particular for ſeuerall perſons in their peculiar calling.</p>
               <p>The generall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Wiſdome haue reſpect to the <hi>Praepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19305:31"/> the foundations, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> offices, and the fruits of wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The first praepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue vnto wiſdome.</note>The <hi>Praeparatiues</hi> vnto wiſdome are two; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> firſt is to exempt &amp; fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a mans ſelfe both out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardly from popular &amp; multitudinary errors &amp; opinions, and inwardly from paſſions: the firſt may be auoided by fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vulgar rabble &amp; their headlong deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and by frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the company of the more iudicious; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond by a diſcuſſiue prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caution or praemeditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereby a man flyeth or extinguiſheth whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer might kindle or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame his paſſions, and by a conſtant reſolution
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19305:31"/> of minde, whereby a man (foreſeeing the euent) is forearmed to beare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſion or diſtemper whatſoeuer happeneth.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue vnto Wiſdome,<note place="margin">The ſecond prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue vnto Wiſdome.</note> is for a man to maintaine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a free and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous libertie of minde: which libertie is twofold, of the iudgement and the will; the libertie of the iudgement is to iudge indifferently of al things, without reſolution or peremptorie affirmation or condemnation of any thing, and not to bee ſo foole-hardie to binde or wedde a mans ſelfe to any opinion, but that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſounder reaſon hee
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19305:32"/> may bee ready to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that which is more true, honeſt, profitable, accommodating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe outwardly to that which is <hi>de facto,</hi> but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing inwardly of that which is <hi>de iure.</hi> The li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the will conſiſts in managing our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mildly and diſcreetly with reaſon and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and paſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt foundation of Wiſdome</note>The foundations of Wiſdome are likewiſe two: the firſt is a true, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall, and inward ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, which is a firme and ſtrong diſpoſition of the will to follow the counſell of reaſon in that which is honeſt and iuſt;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19305:32"/> not for formalitie ſake, (according to the faſhion of the world) nor for the maintenance of a mans honour, credit, reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nor for feare of the law, magiſtrate, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, diſpleaſure, or any ſuch caſuall or ſiniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, for this is onely a bare outward action, and no inward probitie, but this honeſt wiſe man muſt both bee and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently deſire to bee an honeſt man in his heart and minde, <hi>&amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiùs eum eſſe quàm videri.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Wiſdome is to haue a certaine end and forme of life, that is,<note place="margin">The ſecond foundation of Wiſdome</note> for a man to make choice of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19305:33"/> ſuch a calling whereunto his particular nature is moſt inclinable, for <hi>illud quemque decet quod ſuum eſt maximè, that becomes euery man beſt, to which he is naturally moſt addicted,</hi> therefore it behoues eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to know two things, firſt his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſpoſition, his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie and abilitie, to what he is moſt prone, and for what he is vnapt; ſecondly the nature of the profeſſion hee hath propoſed to himſelfe, comparing them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the end hee may ſee how his nature agrees with his profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and carry himſelfe in his vocation with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19305:33"/> and delight.</p>
               <p>The offices of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are ſix;<note place="margin">The firſt office of Wiſdome.</note> the firſt is to ſtudie true religion and pietie, which princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally conſiſts in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue knowledge of God and our ſelues, of God for his honour and glory, of our ſelues for our owne ſaluation. Now this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion muſt not bee for faſhion ſake, to goe with a Bible vnder the arme, as dogges goe to Church for company; nor yet ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall, for ſo a man may be religious and wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked, and bee (according to the prouerbe) <hi>a Saint at Church, and a Deuill at home;</hi> nor only in word and beleefe, for ſo one
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19305:34"/> may be more then a man by confeſſion, and worſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then a ſwine in his life: but this Religion muſt be maried to an eſſentiall honeſtie, cauſing a man to bee honeſtly religious and religiouſly honeſt, both inwardly in ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and truth, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond office of Wiſdome.</note>The ſecond office of Wiſdome is diſcreetly to gouerne our deſires and pleaſures; not wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing them after the opinion of the preciſer ſort, that endeuour ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to ſlide through this life like a fiſh in the water, and hold their breath at all honeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19305:34"/> as if they were in a place of infection; wee muſt rather manage our deſires and pleaſures well, and learne to make vſe and benefit of the world, and not enioy it; and this we ſhal the more eaſily attaine if wee deſire but a little, naturally, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, and by relation: 1. a little, that is, to pull in the raynes of our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, and to reſtraine our ſelues from abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and delicacie; and this is the neereſt way to content, <hi>nihil enim inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n habeas, an non concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcas, not to deſire and to enioy is one.</hi> 2. Naturally, that is, to deſire not things ſuperfluous, arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19305:35"/> and pleaſing to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fantaſie (for theſe are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and beyond na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) but things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and moſt expedient both for our bodies and our humane condition 3. Moderately and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exceſſe, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of another, without his ſcandall, loſſe, preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and in reſpect of our ſelues, without the loſſe or hindrance of our health, leaſure, functions, affaires, reputation, duty. 4. By relation, that is, to propoſe vnto our ſelues a certaine end of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and pleaſures, and to terminate them in our ſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third office of Wiſdome.</note>The third office of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19305:35"/> is with an equall, manly, and ſettled coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to beare the ſmiles and frownes of proſperous and aduerſe fortune; <hi>hoc enim eſt benè ſuſtinere, &amp; abſtinere benè, this is well to ſuſtaine the euill of aduerſitie, and well to abſtaine from the ſugred baits of pleaſure and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie:</hi> not like the vulgar, that thinke there is no ſurfetting with hony, no rockes able to ſplit the floating ſhip of proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; wee muſt rather fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the aduice of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, <hi>&amp; ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in ſecundis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidere, nec in aduerſis defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ſed ſemper erigere animum ſupra minas &amp; promiſſa fortunae; wee must
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19305:36"/> neither preſume in proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor deſpaire in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but alwayes eleuate our ſpirit aboue the threats and promiſes of fortune.</hi> Wee ſhall the better carry our ſelues in proſperitie, if we conſider well the nature of it, firſt that riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and the fauours of fortune are improperly called goods, ſince they are common as well to the bad as the good, and neither make the one better, nor reforme the other; ſecondly that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie is like a honied poiſon, and therefore we ſhould bee then moſt carefull and learne to mortifie our preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to bridle our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19305:36"/> and retaine our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. And for Aduerſitie, <hi>quoniam ipſa vita eſt fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iae ludibrium, &amp; omnia ad quae gemimus, quae expaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcimus, tributa vitae ſunt; ſince our life is but the play-game of fortune, and all things that grieue and afflict vs are but the tributes of life, and incident to our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane condition,</hi> we ſhould therefore make a virtue of neceſſitie, and arme our ſelues with patience quietly to endure them: and the more eaſily wee may doe it if we conſider well the nature and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of aduerſities and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, whether they be true and naturall, as ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pouertie, and the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19305:37"/> like, or imaginarie and fantaſticall. In reſpect of the nature of aduerſitie wee may eaſily endure it, 1. becauſe it is in it ſelfe no euill, but in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the vulgar; 2. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is common to all, though after a diuers manner, to the wiſe and godly as matter of good and inſtruction, to fooles and reprobates as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euill and deſpaire; 3. becauſe it toucheth but the leſſer and outward part of man, and cannot make him vicious, nor rob him of his probitie and virtue, though it make him poore, ſicke, and afflicted. In reſpect of the cauſe of aduerſitie
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19305:37"/> we muſt conſider that it is either our owne ſinne, the iuſtice and anger of God, or the policie of the world. And now the face of aduerſitie is thus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masked, it will appeare with a more gentle aſpect, and we may auoid or mitigate it by theſe two meanes, firſt by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing honeſt and vertuous, (for ſuch a man is more peaceable in aduerſitie then a wicked man in proſperitie) ſecondly by premeditation and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſing the worſt, that ſo we may be fore-armed to beare with patience any thing that may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen; <hi>nam quae alij diu pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo leuia faciunt, ſapiens
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19305:38"/> leuia facit diu cogitando, that which others make light by long ſuffering, a wiſe man maketh eaſie by long cogitation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth office of Wiſdome.</note>The fourth office of Wiſdome is to obſerue the lawes, cuſtomes, and ceremonies of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; firſt authoritie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a meſſenger from heauen, whether it bee ſoueraigne in the Prince, or ſubalterne in his lawes and ordinances; ſecondly ceremonie and the cuſtome of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, becauſe by vſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation or toleration it is growne to be a law; therefore obey the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and the law, but not ſeruilely; obſerue ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19305:38"/> but not ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly; and (if thou canſt with a ſafe conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) conforme thy ſelfe outwardly to that which is in practiſe, though thou condemne it in thy iudgement, and lend, but not giue thy ſelfe to the world.</p>
               <p>The fift office of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is well and plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to carry our ſelues in company,<note place="margin">The fift office of Wiſdome.</note> whether it be generally with ſtrangers in the ordinary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of the world, or more particularly in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted company; ſuch as we embrace for profit, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or ſome other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; and herein a man muſt a little temporize
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19305:39"/> with the world, and not wholly captiuate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his peculiar incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, <hi>ſed vbicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> opus ſit animum flectere, bend his minde as occaſion ſhall require.</hi> In our common conuerſation wee ſhall the better cary our ſelues if we obſerue theſe rules, 1. for a man to ſpeake lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and modeſtly; 2. not to bee too ſcrupulous in applying himſelfe to the faſhion of the company; 3. not to bee too forward to put out himſelfe and ſhew all that is in him; 4. to be honeſtly curious in enquiring of al things, iudging ſoundly of them, ſo to make vſe and profit by them; 5. not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19305:39"/> with any, eſpecially not our ſuperiours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee owe them re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpect, not our inferiours becauſe the match is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall; 6. not to ſpeake reſolutely or perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in any diſcourſe: ſo by this meanes a man ſhall carry himſelfe well and debonarily towards all, and yet haue his minde ſecret, and keepe himſelfe to himſelfe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>frons aperta, lingua parca, mens clauſa, nulli fidere.</hi> In our particular and more priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation it will be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to obſerue theſe rules, 1. for our aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates to make choice of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19305:40"/> ſuch as are honeſt, wiſe, and dexterious; 2. not to be amazed at the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others though it oppoſe ours, but to iudge ſoundly of it, and if there be cauſe of contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not to bee bold, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, nor bitter; 3. not to bee troubled with the vnciuill behauiour or rude ſpeeches of any, but to beare them manfully, and not anſwer a foole in his follie; 4. in diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and controuerſie to be briefe and methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and to ayme alwaies at the truth, not vſing all the meanes a man may haue, but the beſt and moſt preſſing; 5. in a ieſt to take the preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19305:40"/> by the locke, and to be facete without ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilitie, and touch no mans perſon nor reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for it is a bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change to ſell a friend for a ieſt:</p>
               <p>The ſixt and laſt office of Wiſdome is for a man to carry himſelfe wiſely in his affaires;<note place="margin">The laſt office of Wiſdome.</note> and for introduction hereunto it is neceſſary to know well in what ranke to place the goods ſpirituall and temporall, which are principally eight, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſoure reſpect the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>health, beautie, nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, riches,</hi> and foure the ſoule, <hi>honeſtie, wiſdome, abilitie, ſcience,</hi> and theſe are correſpondent one to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19305:41"/> the other, ſo that health, beautie, nobilitie and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the body are the ſame that honeſtie, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſufficiencie or abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and ſcience in the ſoule; and in vaine ſhall a man ſtudie the precepts of a good life, vnleſſe he know well how to iudge and eſteeme of theſe. Now the rules and beſt helpes to this wiſe carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in our affaires are theſe; 1. To know the nature and humour of the perſon with whom a man hath to deale, that ſo he may turne his ſaile to the winde, and alſo the nature of the buſineſſe he hath in hand, not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficially, but the quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſence
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19305:41"/> of it; 2. to know the true worth and value of things, iudging of them not like the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort by their nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſtrangeneſſe, difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or report, but eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all things (after the manner of the wiſe) firſt inwardly by their true and naturall value, then outwardly by their profit and commoditie; 3 to chuſe well, which choice conſiſts either in good things, to chuſe the moſt honeſt &amp; commodious, or in euil to flie the moſt iniuſt, diſhoneſt, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient: 4 to conſult and take the aduice of a friend, who muſt be firſt honeſt and faithfull, then
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19305:42"/> diſcreet and ſufficient: 5. To ballance a mans ſelfe betweene diſtruſt and aſſurance, not to bee too confident in any man, yet making no ſhew of diſtruſt, but fearing to be deceiued: 6. To make vſe of all occaſions, and herein a man muſt auoid two things, precipitation and raſhneſſe in appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending, moreſitie and ſlackneſſe for ouer-ſlip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping the occaſion, and take it neither when it is greene, nor too ripe, but iuſt when it is offered: 7. To doe nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a good reaſon: 8. To be induſtrious, not rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon fortune, nor contemning it, in all our
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19305:42"/> actions making vertue the captaine, fortune the follower, <hi>virtute duce, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite fortunâ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fruits of Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are two;<note place="margin">The firſt fruit of Wiſdome.</note> the firſt is to keepe a mans ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ready for death; <hi>tam vtiliter viuendum eſt, vt non neſciamus foelicitèr deſiſtere, wee muſt liue ſo profitably, that wee may know how to die happily,</hi> eſteeming of death not like the common people that ſhe it as an euill, nor as ſome that contemne it as a thing of no impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, nor as others that ſeeke and deſire it, <hi>vitam habentes in patientiâ, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in deſiderio, enduring life, and coueting death;</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:19305:43"/> wee muſt follow the wiſe, and neither feare nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire death, but attend it cheerefully as a thing na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, becauſe it is the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the whole Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe; ineuitable, <hi>quia om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes eodem cogimur, becauſe wee are all compeld to die;</hi> profitable, <hi>quia dies mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis aeterninatalis eſt, becauſe the day of our death is the birth-day of eternitie, and the conſummation of our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> Now the meanes to make our ſelues ready for death are theſe, 1. in all our actions to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, 2. euery night to caſt vp our accounts, and to repent earneſtly for the miſdeeds of that day;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19305:43"/> and ſo (our ſinnes being dead before our ſelues) we ſhal haue nothing elſe to doe at the houre of our death but to die.</p>
               <p>The laſt fruit and crowne of Wiſdome is to maintaine our ſelues in a true tranquillitie of ſpirit,<note place="margin">The ſecond fruit of Wiſdome.</note> which is not (as ſome ſuppoſe) a vacancie from all affaires, nor a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull ſolitarineſſe, or a profound careleſneſſe, but a ſweet, firme, and pleaſant eſtate of the ſoule, which no occaſion, buſineſſe, good nor ill accidents can any way al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, trouble, or depreſſe. This is that whereby a wiſe man poſſeſſes and enioyes himſelfe, liues
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19305:44"/> alwayes rich, full of ioy, of peace, of comfort, and content in himſelfe. Not beſotted with vulgar opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, nor enthralled with the tyrannie of paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſions, not raſh in iudging, not violent, not vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in willing; honeſt in his life, delighted in his vocation, liuing truly religious; rectifying his deſires, moderating his pleaſures: not ſwollen in proſperitie, not deiected in aduerſitie; conforming himſelfe to the lawes and cuſtomes of his country; carrying himſelfe wiſely with others, &amp; diſcreetly in his worldly affaires; neither hugging his life, nor fearing nor deſiring
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19305:44"/> his death. Now this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie is that morall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie which is acquired by many habits: the meanes to attaine it are the eleuen laſt handled, and the meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it are two; 1. Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie and a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, <hi>quibus tanquam in publico &amp; teſte coelo viui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, whereby we liue as it were in publike, and haue God for a witneſſe to all our actions,</hi> 2. Alacritie and a couragious conſtancie, whereby a man ſolaceth himſelfe, and raiſeth his ſpirit aboue all chances that may happen, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perturbation or feare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:19305:45"/>
               <head>The third part of this Booke, containing the particular instructions of Wiſdome, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect particular perſons in their ſeuerall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, affaires and accidents.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth now that wee proceede to the laſt part of Wiſdome, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth euery mans par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; and the ſhorteſt way to attaine it is to guide our ſelues by the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19305:45"/> foure Morall or Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall vertues, for theſe haue reſpect to all our humane condition, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to the whole courſe of our life, but eſpecially to the Affaires wherein it is buſied, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to the Perſons, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and Temperance to the Accidents.</p>
               <p>Prudence (which is <hi>Auriga virtutum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prudence in generall deſcribed.</note> 
                  <hi>the Queene and guide of the other vertues</hi>) is the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction &amp; choice of things that are to bee deſired or fled, and conſiſteth in conſulting and delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting well, in iudging and reſoluing well, in accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pliſhing and executing well. And it is diuerſly
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19305:46"/> diſtinguiſht; firſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Perſons, and ſo it is either priuate <hi>in vnico indiuiduo,</hi> or ſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and oeconomicall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a few, or publike and politike among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: ſecondly it is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht in reſpect of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, which are either ordinary and eaſie, or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and extraordinary.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Politike prudence diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note>Of all the reſt the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litike Prudence is moſt difficult, and therefore moſt excellent, and it is either publike or priuate; the publike concerneth the office of a Prince, which is either Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue concerning his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for the State, or Actiue for his action and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19305:46"/> gouernment. The pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Prudence reſpecteth the carriage both of the Prince and of priuate men in difficult affaires and accidents.</p>
               <p>The preparatiue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Prince concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the preparation of prouiſion for a State (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Writers of beſt note and choice,<note place="margin">The prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiue office of a Prince.</note> whom I haue eſpecially followed in this Tract) conſiſteth principally in ſeuen points, <hi>knowledge of the State, Virtue, Carriage, Councell, Treaſure, Forces and Armes, Alliances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The knowledge of the State conſiſteth in two things,<note place="margin">The firſt head of prouiſion for a State</note> to know the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the people and of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19305:47"/> the State, the forme, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, and birth thereof, whether it bee old or new, fallen by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion or election, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Lawes or Armes, of what extent it is, what neighbours, meanes, power it hath; for according to theſe a Prince muſt diuerſly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the Scepter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond head of prouiſion.</note>The ſecond head of prouiſion is the virtue of the Prince, which ſhould be liuely and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary, becauſe hee is moſt eminent and in the eye of all, and becauſe his actions are a law to the people. Now theſe vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are principally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in a Prince, <hi>Pietie,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19305:47"/> Iuſtice, Valour, Clemencie, Liberalitie, Magnanimitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pietie of the Prince is to maintaine Religion, and to depreſſe all innouations and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies therein.</p>
               <p>The Iuſtice of a Prince reſpecteth firſt himſelfe, to be (as neere as may be) the ſame in his life that hee is in his lawes; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly his ſubiects, to cauſe his lawes to bee iuſtly executed towards all, without partialitie and protraction of ſuits. But in the Iuſtice of a Prince we muſt not bee too ſtrict; for (in as much as it is a matter of no ſmall moment well to gouerne a State) it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19305:48"/> for a Prince en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchangeably to aſſume the skinne of the Foxe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Lion, and to doe that for the good and ſafetie of himſelfe and the weale-publike, which in priuate perſons were vicious and vnlawfull: therefore the Politicians haue thought theſe eight things expedient in a Prince, although ſome queſtion the lawfulneſſe; 1. Diſtruſt, to bee vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, to beleeue none, to take heed of all, <hi>ne aditum nocendi perfido praeſtet fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, left too much credulitie make a Traitor.</hi> 2. Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, both in time of warre with the enemie, and in peace with his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19305:48"/> 3. By ſecret practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and intelligences to draw vnto him the hearts and ſeruices of the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and truſtieſt friends of forraine Princes and Lords, and of his owne ſubiects at home; and this is wrought either by perſwaſion, or preſents and penſions. 4. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tletie, to obtaine his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe by equiuocation, circumuention, Letters, embaſſages, and to doe that cloſely which hee may not doe openly. 5. To clip the wings of any one that is like to ſoare too high in the State. 6. In a time of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie and pouertie of the State to take by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19305:49"/> the wealth of the richeſt. 7. To cancell the lawes or priuiledges that are any way preiudiciall to the authoritie of the Prince. 8. To poſſeſſe himſelfe by preuention of a Citie or Prouince commodious for the State, rather then to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer another dangerous neighbour to take it.</p>
               <p>His Valour is a mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie and couragious wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which is required in him for the defence of himſelfe and the State.</p>
               <p>The Clemencie of a Prince is a ſweet kinde of lenitie, and required in him to moderate the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of Iuſtice, and to make him more beloued
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19305:49"/> then feared of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.</p>
               <p>The Liberalitie of a Prince conſiſteth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly in gifts beſtowed, wherein are to bee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered two things, firſt the perſon, who ſhould be a man of deſert, or one that hath done good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to the common-weale; ſecondly the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the gift, which muſt not be exceſſiue, nor at once.</p>
               <p>The Magnanimitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a Prince is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſitie or greatneſſe of courage, <hi>non leuiter iraſci, ſed iniurias deſpicere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignas Caeſaris irâ, not to bee eaſily moued, but to deſpiſe iniuries that are
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19305:50"/> vnworthy the anger of a Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third head of prouiſion.</note>The third head of prouiſion is the Carriage of the Prince, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth 1. his perſon, wherein ſhould bee a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſticall and venerable grauitie marching be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt feare and loue; 2. his reſidence, which ſhould bee in ſome glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and eminent place, and (if it may be) in the midſt of the State; 3. his conuerſation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, which ſhould bee rare, <hi>quia maieſtati ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior ex longinquo reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, becauſe the rareneſſe of a Princes preſence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures the greater reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:19305:50"/>
               <p>The fourth head of prouiſion is Councell,<note place="margin">The fourth head of prouiſion.</note> wherein a Prince ſhould make vſe 1. of ſuch as are honeſt and faithfull, 2. ſuch as are ancient, ripe, and well experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the State; 3. ſuch as are free from flatterie, <hi>ne cum fortunâ Principis potiùs loquantur quàm cum ipſo;</hi> 4. ſuch as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, without opinatiue obſtinacie or yeelding to the humour of another; 5. ſuch as are ſecret. And theſe Counſellers muſt be choſen either by the iudgement and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Prince, or by their publike eſteeme and reputation.</p>
               <p>The fift head of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion<note place="margin">The fift head of Prouiſion.</note>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:19305:51"/> is Treaſure the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of the State, which conſiſteth in three points, the foundation, emploiment, reſeruation thereof.</p>
               <p>For the foundation of the Treaſurie theſe are the meanes, 1. not to alienate the publike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenew of the State; 2. to employ well the ſpoiles made vpon the enemie; 3. preſents, tributes, and donations of friends, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and ſubiects; 4. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts vpon merchandiſe in Dockes and Hauen Townes, prouided firſt that there bee no tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for life, nor of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought wares, that the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19305:51"/> Subiects may be furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſet on worke, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly that the ſtranger bee more charged then the Subiect. And theſe are the meanes for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the Treaſurie moſt iuſt and approued; there are alſo other meanes, but not ſo vſuall, as the emploiment of the Exchequer coine to ſome ſmall profit, and ſubſidies and loanes of ſubiects in a time of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie; which loanes muſt be leuied vpon the goods, and not the heads of men, and equally vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all, for it is iniuſtice that ſome ſhould pay all, and others bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:19305:52"/>
               <p>Concerning the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiment of the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, it ſhould bee for the maintenance of the Kings houſe, the pay of men of warre, the wages of Officers, the reward of ſuch as deſerue well of the Common-wealth, the ſuccour of poore, repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Cities, fortifying the Frontiers, mending high-wayes, eſtabliſhing Colledges and publike houſes.</p>
               <p>For the reſeruation of the Treaſurie againſt a time of neceſſitie, the moſt profitable and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way is to lend the coine (as is aforeſaid) with ſome ſmall profit to particular perſons vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19305:52"/> good ſecuritie, and that for a threefold rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; becauſe it increaſeth the Treaſurie, it giues meanes to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to traffike, and ſaues the publike treaſure from the pawes of the inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Courtiers.</p>
               <p>The ſixt head of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion is an armed pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,<note place="margin">The ſixt head of prouiſion for a State.</note> which is either ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary or extraordinary; the ordinary is of two ſorts, the one for the guard of the Kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the other certaine companies maintained in a readineſſe for ſuch ſudden occurrences as may happen: the extra ordinary power is in a time of warre, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19305:53"/> in forces &amp; armes, or a certaine number of people well experienced in the warres, to repreſſe a ſudden rebellion or commotion, either with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in or without the State.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The laſt head of prouiſion for a State.</note>The ſeuenth and laſt head of prouiſion conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in Alliances or Leagues, which are either perpetuall, or limited for a certaine time, or for commerce and traffike only, or elſe for amitie, to be ſworne friends and coadiutors one to the other; and herein it is needfull for a Prince to ioyne in alliance with thoſe that are neighbors and puiſſant, and not to make the league perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19305:53"/> but for certaine yeares, that ſo he may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take away or adde to the Articles, or wholly forſake them, or elſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new the league before it be expired, as need ſhall require.</p>
               <p>THe Actiue office of a Prince concerning his gouernment of the State conſiſteth in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of the loue of the ſubiects,<note place="margin">The actiue office of a Prince.</note> and in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie; the firſt is attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by gentleneſſe and clemencie in comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, beneficence in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding plentie of come and victuall for the ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the meaner people, and liberalitie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19305:54"/> handled in the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of a Prince, which is moſt needfull in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to a new State. The ſecond (which is autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie) is attained not by a tyrannicall crueltie, for the Prince to make his will a law, employing all to his owne profit or pleaſure, not reſpecting the publike good, (for this breedeth hatred and contempt, which both proceed from rigour in puniſhing, or from aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice either in exacting too much or giuing too little) but this authoritie is attained and preſerued 1. by a diſcreet ſeueritie, whereby a good Prince in ſome caſes may doe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19305:54"/> that which beareth a ſhew of tyrannie, <hi>&amp; crudelis eſſe medicus in laethali vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere;</hi> 2. by a couragious conſtancie or a ſtaied re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, enforcing the obſeruation of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent lawes and cuſtomes; 3. by holding the ſterne of the State, the honour and power of comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in his owne hand, not referring all to his Councell.</p>
               <p>Now this Actiue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Prince is either Peaceable or Militarie;<note place="margin">The peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able office of a Prince</note> the Peaceable (by reaſon of the multiplicitie of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires) cannot wholly bee preſcribed, but it conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth partly in auſcultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be well aduertiſed
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19305:55"/> of all things by ſuch as are faithfull, wiſe, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret about him, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of his honour and duty, his defects, &amp; what is done in the State and among the bordering neighbours; and partly in action, 1. to haue a memoriall of the affaires of the State, of the moſt worthy and beſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing perſonage, and of the gifts beſtowed, to whom, wherefore, and how much; 2. to appoint rewards &amp; puniſhments, the one muſt bee done immediately by the Prince, the other ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately by his officers.<note place="margin">The mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Prince.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Militarie Action of a Prince conſiſteth in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19305:55"/> enterpriſing, making and finiſhing warre.</p>
               <p>To make an enterprize iuſt,<note place="margin">Rules in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſing.</note> three things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: firſt that it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced &amp; vndertaken by the Prince: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it bee for a iuſt cauſe, whether defenſiue for the defence of his life, liberty, country, Allies and confederates: or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue, proceeding from ſome former iniury. Thirdly, that it be for a good end, as peace, and quietneſſe, or the like.</p>
               <p>To make warre,<note place="margin">Rules in making warre.</note> three things are required, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, Men, and Rules of warre. The principall munitions of warre are Money, Victualls,<note place="margin">Munition.</note> and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19305:56"/> Armes; both defenſiue, and offenſiue.<note place="margin">Men.</note> The men are to aſſaile and defend, and are eyther Souldiers or Leaders: The Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are diuided into foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and horſe, naturall and ſtrangers, ordinary and ſubſidiary; and theſe muſt be firſt choſen, then diſciplined. In the choice of Souldiers fiue things are to be conſidered: firſt that they betaken out of hard places, and accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to all manner of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor: ſecondly, that they be young &amp; luſty: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of an able body and ſufficient ſtature: fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of a bold and reſolute ſpirit: fiftly (if it may be) of an honeſt condition.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:19305:56"/>
               <p>In the diſcipline of Souldiers two ends are to be propoſed, Valour and Manners, to make the Souldiers valiant &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; to Valour 3. things are needfull. Firſt, daily exerciſe in Armes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, trauell &amp; paines, to learne to digge, to plant a Pallaſide, to order a Barricado, to carry hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burthens, and the like. Thirdly, Order: 1. in the diſtribution of the troopes into Battali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Regiments, Enſigns Camerads: 2. in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of the Campe, diuiding it proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly into quarters, hauing the places, entries, iſſues,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19305:57"/> and lodgings fitted both for horſemen and foote, whereby it may bee eaſie for euery man to find his quarter and place: 3. in the March in the field a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enemy, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one keepe his ranke and bee equally diſtant one from an other: And this order is moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for ſecuring the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and for the facillity of the remoues and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Captaines.</p>
               <p>To Manners (the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of warlike diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline) three things are required: 1 Continency, to depreſſe gluttony, drunkenneſſe, whoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and all looſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality in the Souldiers:
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19305:57"/> 2. Modeſty in words, to ſhun all oſtentation and brauery of ſpeech: 3. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence to keepe their hands from violence, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage and robbery.</p>
               <p>This of the Souldiers. The Captains are of two ſorts, the Generall, who muſt be either the Prince himſelfe or his deputy; and the Subalterne Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Companies. In the Generall this is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite: 1. that hee be wiſe, and well experienced in the Art military: 2. that hee be cold and ſtayed, free from precipitation and temerity: 3. that hee bee vigilant and actiue, teaching by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:19305:58"/>
               <p>The rules of war (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the third thing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make warre) by reaſon of the diuers oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall and certaine: but the generall aduiſements reſpect eyther the whole time of warre, the fight, the ranged battailes, or the battalles beeing ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rules of warre.</note>The rules of the whole time of warre are theſe: 1. carefully to meete the occaſions, and to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the enemy in his: 2. To make profit of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours that flye abroad, but not to bee troubled with them to alter a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution grounded vppon good reaſon: 3. For ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19305:58"/> ſide to be too confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in his own ſtrength, nor to preſume vpon the weakneſſe of his enemy, for this breedeth neglect and careleſneſſe: 4. To enquire carefully of the enemy; of the nature, capacity, and deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Chieftaine; of the nature, manners, and kinde of life of the enemies; of the ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the places, and the nature of the Country.</p>
               <p>Touching the fight theſe circumſtances are to be obſerued: 1. The time, which muſt be ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and in neceſſity, the viands or treaſure fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the men beginning to diſtaſt the wars, or the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19305:59"/> like: 2. The place, not within his owne territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, vnleſſe the enemy be already entered, and then he muſt not hazard the battell till he haue an other army in ſupply: and for the field, it muſt bee conſidered whether it be fitter for himſelfe or the enemy, as the Champion is beſt for the Caualary, ſtreight and narrow pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſet with piles, full of ditches and trees for the Infantery. 3. The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the fight is to bee conſidered, and heere the moſt aduantagious is the beſt, whether it be by ſurprize, ſubtlety, ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, cloſe and convert, fayning to feare, ſo to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19305:59"/> the enemy, or by watching his ouerſights, the better to preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
               <p>For Ranges of Battailes, theſe things are required: 1. A comely ordering of the men: 2 A hidden ſupply alwaies in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to aſtoniſh the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my vnawares: 3. To be firſt in the field and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in battell aray: 4. A cheerefull countenance of the Generall and the Captaines: 5. An orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to encourage the ſouldiers, laying open the honour of valour, and the iuſtice of their cauſe.</p>
               <p>The Battailes beeing ioyned, if the Army wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19305:60"/> the Generall muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate them by his own example, and diſcharge the duety of a reſolute Leader, and if the fielde be his, hee muſt ſtay his Souldiers, leaſt in purſuit of the enemy, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and ſcatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and ſo the vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed gather head and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome them. If he be vanquiſhed, he muſt not be aſtoniſhed, but renew his forces, make a new Leuie, put good garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in his ſtrongeſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and hope to better his fortunes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third head of the military action of a Prince.</note>The third head of this Military action is to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Warre by Peace, which muſt bee conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19305:60"/> vpon good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt conditions, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fraud and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; otherwaies it were better to die in the bedde of honour then to ſerue diſhonourably.</p>
               <p>The rules heerein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect firſt the vanquiſhed who ſhould continue ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and make ſhew of ſecurity and reſolution: Secondly, the vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who ought not to be ouer-hardly perſwaded to peace: 1. Becauſe an old enemy groweth cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; dangerous: 2. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the continuance of warre is burthenſome to the ſtate: 3. <hi>Quia tutior certa pax ſperatâ victoriâ Becauſe a certaine Peace is
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19305:61"/> better then a hoped for vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Prudence required in difficult af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires and ill accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note>THe ſecond part of Prudence is Priuate, which reſpecteth the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage both of the Prince, and of priuate men in difficult affaires and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; theſe affairs &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents are either publike or priuate, whereof ſome are to come and threaten vs, and are doubtfull and ambiguous: other pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent and preſſing vs, and are difficult &amp; dangerous.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ill accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to come.</note>In thoſe euils that are to come and threaten vs; the beſt way to oppoſe a mans ſelf ſtrongly againſt the accident, ſo to breake the necke of it by his vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gilancy
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19305:61"/> before it come, or elſe to reſolue with himſelf patiently to beare whatſoeuer happeneth.</p>
               <p>In thoſe that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and preſſe vs (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee ſome preſent vnlucky accident,<note place="margin">Jll acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</note> or the remembrance of any that is paſt, or ſome vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſion that troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth) the beſt way is to diuert a mans thoughts to ſome other obiect, ſo hee may leſſen, if not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh his griefe.</p>
               <p>In ambiguous affaire (as in the choice of two things that ſeeme equally good or euill,<note place="margin">Ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires.</note> ſo that the inability to chooſe the beſt breedeth anxiety &amp; perplexity) the ſafeſt way
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:19305:62"/> is to leane to that part that hath moſt honeſtie and iuſtice, as a traueller doubting of the neereſt way muſt take the ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Dangerous affaires.</note>In difficult and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous affaires, a man muſt be both wiſe to know the nature, and to foreſee the euent of the accident, and couragious to auoide it by induſtrie or aide.</p>
               <p>Now of thoſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents that are difficult and dangerous, ſome are ſecret and hidden, others manifeſt and open: thoſe that are hidden and moſt dangerous are two,<note place="margin">Coni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration, which is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie of one, or many
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19305:62"/> againſt the perſon of the Prince, and Treaſon,<note place="margin">Treaſon.</note> which is a conſpiracy or enterprize againſt a place or company, although we commonly call them Traytors that pretend it to the crowne. Now a Prince muſt endeuour to preuent theſe two daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous accidents by theſe meanes: 1. By Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie (for this is the beſt ſafe-guard of a Prince:) 2. By a ſubordinate vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancie, that is, by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret enquiry of ſuch as are diſcreet and faithfull about him, who are his eyes and eares: 3 By ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no ſhew of diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their plots, but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the euent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19305:63"/> aſtoniſhment: 4. By the rigorous puniſhment of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpirators, which puniſhments muſt bee ſometimes ſudden, if the number bee ſmall and knowne, ſometimes dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, to ſeeke by tortures to know the confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Popular commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>Of thoſe dangerous accidents that are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and open, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions of the People are the greateſt, and theſe are of many ſorts; when the inſurrection is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues, it is eyther a ſudden tumult or a faction; when it is a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt the Prince, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> State or Magiſtrate, it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eyther Sedition, Rebe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lion,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19305:63"/> or ciuill warre.</p>
               <p>Sudden Tumults are nothing but commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the people raiſed in a heate,<note place="margin">Sudden tumults.</note> and in this caſe the beſt way to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage the people is to procure ſome eminent man, reuerenc't for his grauity, place, and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to ſpeake to the people, firſt in the ſmooth calme of mildneſſe and perſwaſion, then (if that preuaile not) in the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of authority.</p>
               <p>Faction or Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy is a complot or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation of one againſt an other among the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects;<note place="margin">Faction.</note> ariſing commonly from ambition or hatred; and in this caſe (if it bee
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19305:64"/> betweene great houſes, cities, or communities) the Prince himſelfe muſt endeuour to make Peace betweene them, eyther by gentle entreaties or threatning, or elſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point his arbitrators; and if the faction be between great multitudes that wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not bee appeaſed by iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the Prince muſt employ his force to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sedition.</note>Sedition is a violent commotion of a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude againſt a Prince or Magiſtrate, ariſing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly from oppreſſion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feare eyther of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or puniſhment for ſome hainous offence; ſometimes from a licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19305:64"/> liberty, ſometimes from want and neceſſity. Now the beſt meanes to appeaſe this ſeditious rout are theſe; firſt (as it was aduiſed concerning ſudden tumults) to cauſe men of authority to ſhew themſelues and ſpeak vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, who muſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to diſſolue them by hope and feare, drawing vnto them (if that helpe not) ſome few of them vnder hand by ſecret re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and promiſes, ſo to haue intelligence of their carriages and purpoſes, yeelding to the reſt in doubtfull termes ſome part of their demaund, which may afterwards iuſtly bee reuoked. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19305:65"/> to aſtoniſh them with the ſight of an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med power, but not to depreſſe them ſo, vnleſſe neceſſity compell.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rebellion.</note>Rebellion is an inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prince becauſe of his tyrannie, eyther in his wrongfull vſurpation of the Crowne, or his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt and violent domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and gouernment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lawes and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, though ſomtimes but ſuppoſed. Now if a Prince feare rebellion, the beſt remedy is to ſhun the cauſe: therefore let him bee wiſe as a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, but innocent as a Doue.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ciuill war.</note>Ciuill warre is a preſſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19305:65"/> or conduct of Armes by the ſubiects, ariſing from one of theſe popular publique commotions, which hath now fortified it ſelfe, and gotten an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie trayne and forme of war; And it hath two cauſes, the one ſecret and vnknowne, the other the generall corruption of manners, whereby men of baſe and diſſolute con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition care not to ouer whelm themſelues in the ruine of the State. Now to extinguiſh this fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand of a State, there are but two meanes, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and victory; the latter is dangerous: And the other is not alwaies ſafe as without great cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:19305:66"/> This is of the carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the Prince in theſe dangerous commotions of the people.<note place="margin">How par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons ſhould car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in theſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note> Now pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſons in theſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular and publike com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions and inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons may carrie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues after a twofolde manner, eyther as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, and then (if they bee men of publike charge and credit) they ought to ioyn themſelues to the better part; or elſe they may carrie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as no partakers, and then (if they be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men of a lower de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) the beſt way is to retire themſelues to ſome peaceable and ſecure place during the diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19305:66"/> carrying themſelues eyther as commons, in their wordes and actions beeing offenſiue to ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part; or as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors arbitrating friendly and indifferentlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them: And in this caſe a man muſt be ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Neuter nor a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee.</p>
               <p>Now in Priuate diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions betweene man and man,<note place="margin">How in priuate diſſentions.</note> it is eaſie for one to carry himſelfe loyallie, if hee ingage not himſelfe more to one then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and report nothing but things indifferent, that may ſerue in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to both parts.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19305:67"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iuſtice.</note>THE ſecond virtue whereby wee muſt guide our ſelues is <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> which teacheth how to giue to euery one his due; this reſpecteth the Perſons, and compriſeth our duty towards God, our ſelues, and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Our duty towards God I haue already tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the tract of pietie.<note place="margin">The duty of man towards himſelfe.</note> Our duty towards our ſelues is contained tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout this whole booke; in the firſt part ſhewing the knowledge of our ſelues; in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond preſcribing the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rules of wiſdome; and more particularly in this laſt part, eſpecially
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19305:67"/> in the ſubſequent virtues of Fortitude and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. But more exactly the duty of man towards himſelfe conſiſteth in gouerning his Spirit, his Body, his Goods. The motions of the ſpirit are reduced to two, to thinke and deſire, proceeding from the iudgement and the will: therefore wee muſt be carefull to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne theſe two well. Firſt the vnderſtanding, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it from ſottiſhneſſe and childiſh vanities, and from fantaſticall and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd opinions; ſecondly the will, ſubduing it to the nod of reaſon, not ſuffering it to be led by opinion, paſſion, ſenſe.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:19305:68"/>
               <p>For the Body (in as much as the Spirit is to it as the husband to the wife) wee owe it our care and aſſiſtance; wee muſt therefore nouriſh, not pamper it, making the Spirit Lord ouer it, not a Tyrant, not a Seruant.</p>
               <p>Concerning Goods or riches, wee ought to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to keepe, to employ them well; 1. deſiring, not louing them; 2. ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them, but not by bad meanes or the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of another; 3. not reiecting them entring at an honeſt gate, but recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them willingly into our houſes, not our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; 4. employing them honeſtly and diſcreetly
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19305:68"/> to the good of our ſelues and others; 5. not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing if they bee loſt or ſtollen, but ſuffering them to depart by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, not with our hearts.</p>
               <p>Our duty towards our neighbour is either gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall containing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon duties of all towards all,<note place="margin">The duty of man towards man.</note> or particular contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the particular duties of ſeuerall perſons by ſpeciall obligation.<note place="margin">Common duties.</note> The generall duty of all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards al comprehendeth Amitie and Friendſhip, and the offices thereof, which are Faith and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, Veritie and free Admonition, Benefits and Thankfulneſſe.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:19305:69"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Amitie &amp; friendſhip.</note>Amitie or Friendſhip by the Ancients is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed into <hi>naturall, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable, hoſpitall,</hi> and <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous;</hi> by the Modernes otherwayes, firſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the cauſes of it, which are Nature, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, Profit, Pleaſure; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in reſpect of the perſons, and that in three kindes; either in a direct line betweene Superiours and Inferiours, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Princes and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, Tutors and Pupils, Maſters and Seruants, which cannot properly be called Friendſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the diſparitie and obligation betweene them, which hindereth
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19305:69"/> familiar communication and inwardneſſe; or in a collaterall line betweene equals, which is either Naturall, betweene bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſiſters, and couſins, (which is likewiſe imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by reaſon of the bond of nature) or Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie betweene friends and companions, and this is truly friendſhip. Or elſe it is mixt and matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, which is partly in a direct line becauſe of the ſuperioritie of the husband and the inferio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the wife, and partly in a collaterall line, being both compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and equals; and this is alſo imperfect, both by reaſon of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:19305:70"/> and conſtraint of the bond after mariage, and the weakneſſe of the wife, who is no way corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent in conference and communication, of thoughts &amp; iudgements. Thirdly Friendſhip is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in reſpect of the degrees and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, and ſo there is a Common and a Perfect Friendſhip; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is quickly attained, the Perfect in a long time; that may bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene many, this onely betweene two: the one is capable of reſtraints and exceptions, according to their preſence, abſence, merits, good deeds, and the like; the other is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:19305:70"/> the ſame; the firſt is attained (as ſome haue obſerued) by ſpeaking things pleaſant and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things profitable, the latter onely by a liuely and reciprocall virtue: ſo that Common Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is nothing but fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie or a priuate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, but the true and Perfect conſiſteth in a ſympathie of humours and wils, with one onely who is another ſelfe, and betweene two that are but one. And it is a free and vniuerſall confuſion of two ſoules: the words are emphaticall; 1. a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of foules, importing the inſeparabilitie of the vnion betwixt them,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:19305:71"/> 2. free and voluntarie, built vpon the pure choice of the will, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; 3. vniuerſall, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception of goods, honours, iudgements, thoughts, wils, and life it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Faith and Fidelitie.</note>Now follow the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Friendſhip; the firſt is Fidelitie or Faith, which is a cloſet of the ſecrets of another; and it reſpecteth firſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, both him that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth faith, of whom is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that he haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to doe it either of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe or by the leaue and approbation of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and alſo him to whom it is giuen, who
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:19305:71"/> muſt carefully keepe it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nleſſe he receiue it not, or the other breake firſt: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>econdly the ſubiect of this faith is to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which muſt bee of things iuſt and poſſible; thirdly the manner of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and receiuing it, which muſt be volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and freely, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fraud, treacherie, or ſurpriſe.</p>
               <p>The ſecond office of Friendſhip is a true and free Admonition,<note place="margin">Veritie and free admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are to bee conſidered the time, place, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of admoniſhing; 1. the time, not in a time of mirth, for this were to trouble, nor of griefe and aduerſitie, for this
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:19305:72"/> were to heape ſorrow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on affliction, <hi>frangere, non emendare;</hi> 2. the place, which muſt be in ſecret, not before com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; 3. the manner of admoniſhing, which muſt be 1. without paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 2. without flatterie and diſſimulation, out of an honeſt careleſſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and freedome of heart; 3. vſing generall tearmes, and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending a mans ſelfe in the ſame fault; 4. expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the fault in better words then the nature of the offence doth require; 5. to beginne with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, and end with profers of ſeruice and helpe, and not to be
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:19305:72"/> gone as ſoone as the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition is ended, but to ſtay and fall into ſome common and pleaſant diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>The third office of Friendſhip conſiſteth in benefits, obligation,<note place="margin">Benefits &amp; thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> and thankfulneſſe; theſe three are linkt one in the other, and may well bee compriſed in this word Obligation, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth liberalitie, friendſhip, almeſdeedes, and whatſoeuer is chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and humane. For there is an Actiue and a Paſſiue obligation; the Actiue bindeth Parents, Princes, and Superiours (either by law or nature) to doe good to them that
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:19305:73"/> are committed to their charge, and generally thoſe that haue meanes to helpe them that are in want. Now there is a two-fold manner of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefiting or doing good; by profiting, and by plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; ſo are there two ſorts of good turnes, the one duties proceeding from this naturall or lawfull obligation, the other free and voluntarie good deeds done out of pure affection: and of theſe benefits or good turnes ſuch are moſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as proceed either from one whom a man is inclined to loue without this occaſion, or ſuch as come from one that is
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:19305:73"/> bound to the receiuer, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch as may bee eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited. Now in doing a good turne theſe rules are to be obſerued, 1. to doe it willingly and from a heartie affection; 2. wiſely, without oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without the offence of another; 3. ſpeedily, when there is neede; 4. without hope of reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; 5. according to the intent of the receiuer, and then if it bee to ſuccour his want, weakneſſe, ſhame, or neceſſitie, it muſt be done priuately; 6. not to repent of his good deed; 7. not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect it to the receiuer, not to twit him or hit him in the teeth with it, as
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:19305:74"/> the vulgar ſpeake.</p>
               <p>The other part of an obligation is Paſſiue, which is nothing but a thankfulneſſe for a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit receiued; and herein a man muſt obſerue foure things; 1. to receive the benefit cheerefully, 2. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to remember it, 3. to publiſh it, 4. to make a recompence; which muſt bee done 1. willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 2. not too ſpeedily, but vpon ſome good oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; 3. with vſurie, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the benefit recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, yet alwayes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging a mans ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted; 4. if a man bee vnable to requite, to ſhew alwayes teſtimonies of his thankfulneſſe.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:19305:74"/>
               <p>The ſecond part of our duty towards our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is ſpeciall,<note place="margin">Speciall duties.</note> including the particular duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired betweene ſeuerall perſons by ſpeciall obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; and theſe duties are either Priuate or Publike, the Priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the iuſtice obſerued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Families betweene the Husband and the Wife, Parents and Children, Maſters and Seruants.</p>
               <p>The duties betweene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he man and the wife are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ither common &amp; equall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o both,<note place="margin">The duty of maried folkes.</note> conſiſting in an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntire loyaltie, fidelitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommunitie, care and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ouer their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie and the goods of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e houſe, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:19305:75"/> of all things, on Particular, reſpecting firſt themſelues, ſecondly their domeſticall huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands duty</note>Firſt of the husband this is required, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his wife in thoſe things that concerne he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> duty, her honour, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good; to loue, to nouriſh to cloath her, to cohabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with her.<note place="margin">The wifes duty.</note> Secondly, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the wife this is required to honour her husban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as her Lord, to humou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, to bee obedient i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things iuſt and lawfull, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> keepe the houſe, to em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ploy her time in the pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiſe of huſwifery, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be ſilent, that is, not ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>katiue, but to learne ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:19305:75"/> and when to ſpeake. Thirdly in domeſticall or houſhold husbandrie this is expedient,<note place="margin">Houſhold husbandry.</note> 1. to buy and ſell all things at the beſt times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; 2. to prouide firſt for neceſſitie, cleanlines, order; 3. to take care that the goods of the houſe be not ſpoiled nor loſt; 4. to learne to make a good ſhew with a little coſt; 5. for a man to know pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely the value of his meanes, and to liue vnder his eſtate; 6. to haue an eye and care ouer all, for the eye of the Maſter ſats the horſe and the land.</p>
               <p>The duty of Parents and Children is recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally naturall,<note place="margin">The duty of parents.</note> and hath
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:19305:76"/> reſpect firſt to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, ſecondly to the Children. The duty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Parents reſpecteth 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Infancie, 2. their Youth, 3. their Carriage towards them at mens and womens eſtate.</p>
               <p>In the Infancie of the childe this muſt bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, 1. the nurſe muſt bee either the mother (which is moſt naturall) or a woman that is young and of a hot and dri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> complexion; 2. it muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be fed with creame ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with hony and a little ſalt; 3. it muſt bee accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed by little and little to the aire, to heat and cold.</p>
               <p>In the Youth of the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:19305:76"/> childe, as ſoone as it is able to goe and ſpeake, and the faculties of the minde are awakened, (which beginne about the fourth or fift yeare) it is the duty of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to inſtruct it well, and to ſeaſon this new veſſell with a good and wholeſome tincture. Now theſe inſtructions are either Common or Particular; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon are theſe, 1. carefully to guard the eyes and eares of the childe, that none ſpeake or doe any thing that is euill in his ſight or hearing; 2. to procure good Tutors or Inſtructors, who muſt bee fuller of wiſdome
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:19305:77"/> then Pedanticall ſcience, and ſuch as accord in opinion and their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of proceeding, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mildly without ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and rigour. Now there is no better way of inſtruction then often to examine the ſcholler, and to make him giue his opinion, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a reaſon of his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: and touching the bookes to bee read, they muſt be of noble and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious matters teaching the knowledge of our humane condition, and ſuch as reforme the will and direct the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, teaching the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and virtue, what to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:19305:77"/> flie, what to deſire.</p>
               <p>The Particular inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of youth conſiſt in the forming of the ſpirit, the ordering of the body, the ruling of the manners. In forming the ſpirit of the childe a man muſt aime both at the End and the Meanes of inſtruction. The end of inſtruction is to build vp the minde in knowledge, honeſtie, virtue, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and the aduiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this point are two, firſt not to endeuour ſo much to inflame the imagination and ſtuffe the memorie, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the iudgement and the will; but to ſtudie more for wiſdome then
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:19305:78"/> ſcience, becauſe wiſdome is farre better then ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and becauſe theſe two are much different, eſpecially by reaſon of the contrarietie of their temperatures, for ſcience is in the memorie, which requireth a moiſt temper of the braine, wiſdome in the vnderſtanding which requireth it to bee drie: ſo that ſcience is nothing but an accumulation of an acquired good, or a collection of what is ſeene, heard, read; but wiſdome is the rule of the ſoule, the guide of our thoughts, deſires, opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, words, actions. The ſecond aduice in this point is this; not to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:19305:78"/> the opinions and knowledge of other men for oſtentation or report, but for profit, to make them his owne, as the Bee extracts the hony from the flower; and in reading other mens writings not to taske the memorie to retaine the leafe, the place, the chapter, but the ſumme and marrow of the booke. Now of Sciences the beſt are the Naturall that ſhew what wee are, and the Morall that ſhew what we ſhould bee, vnder which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the <hi>Oeconomickes, Politickes, Hiſtories.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Meanes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction (which is the ſecond thing to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:19305:79"/> in forming the minde of the ſcholler) is two fold, the one by word of mouth, and that either by precepts or conference; the other by example, both from the good by imitation, and from the bad by diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from them in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and life. And theſe two wayes of profiting by ſpeech and example are drawne either from the liuing by diſcourſe and frequentation of their company, or from the dead by reading their bookes.</p>
               <p>In ordering the Body theſe are the rules, 1. to keepe the childe from pride and delicacy in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell;
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:19305:79"/> 2. to vſe him to a moderation in ſleeping, eating and drinking; 3. to accuſtome him to heate and cold, labour and paines.</p>
               <p>In ruling the Manners a man muſt take care to rate vp in his child thoſe things that are euill, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting in him firſt all ſwearing, lying, ſottiſh ſhame, hiding the face, houlding downe the head, bluſhing at euery queſtion, and weeping at euery ſharpe worde: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly all affectation in habit, ſpeech, gate, and geſture: Thirdly all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate ſullenneſſe, that the childe neuer haue his will by froward or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:19305:80"/> meanes.</p>
               <p>And as a man muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the euill, ſo hee muſt endeuour to kindle in his childe the ſparkes of goodneſſe, ingrafting in his heart, firſt the feare of God, by making him reuerence his name, and admire his wiſdome, his power, his workes; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly ingenuity &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, teaching him to bee honeſt for the loue of vertue, and not for any ſiniſter reſpect; thirdly, modeſty in behauiour towards all, whether they bee his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, equals, or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours eyther in conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſufficiencie; fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, affability in company
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:19305:80"/> to carry himſelfe courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly towards all, yet let him know euen the moſt licentious behauiors, but teach him to abſtaine, not for want of courage, but will.</p>
               <p>In the carriage of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents toward their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren at mens &amp; womens eſtate (which is the fourth and laſt point of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) it behooues them to receiue their children (if they bee diſcreet and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable) into their ſociety and part of their goods, and to admitt them into their councell, their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, thoughts, deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; the knowledge of their worldly affaires; not practiſing the auſtere
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:19305:81"/> faſhion of ſome parents, that alwaies keepe their children vnder their gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; they carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſeuerely towards them, reſtraine them of liberty, pinch them in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, and vpon euery diſpleaſing occaſion euer fright, them with the bug beare of a ſmall annuity after their deceaſe, ſo to keepe them in awe and ſubiection: But this is the way for a man to bee feared, not loued of his children, and to ſhew himſelfe a Tyrant, not a Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The duty of chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dren.</note>Now the duty of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren towards their Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rents conſiſteth princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallie in 5. points, 1. To
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:19305:81"/> reuerence them both out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in ſpeech, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and geſture, and inwardly in opinion and eſtimation: 2. To obey them in all commands that are iuſt and honeſt; 3. To ſuccour them in want, ſickneſſe, age, and impotency if neede ſhall require; 4. To attempt nothing in marriage, or any other matter of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance without their conſent and aduiſe; 5. To beare with their teſtie hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours &amp; imperfections, &amp; to endure gently thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeuerity and rigour.</p>
               <p>The duties of Maſters and Seruants are theſe,<note place="margin">The duty of maſters.</note> 1. the Maſter muſt ſeeke to be more beloued then
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:19305:82"/> feared of his ſeruants; 2. to haue an eye ouer them; 3. to inſtruct them in matters of religion; 4. to vſe them gently, not cruelly; and yet it is needfull for a Maſter of a family ſometimes to bee angry with his ſeruants obſeruing theſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; 1. that it bee not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, nor vpon ſlight oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; 2. that it be not in a murmuring or ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling manner behind their backes, nor vpon vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties; 3. that it be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily in the nicke of the offence, and ſerious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out commixture of laugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, that ſo it may bee a profitable chaſtiſement for what is paſt, &amp; a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:19305:82"/> for what is to come. And for Seruants,<note place="margin">The duty of ſeruants.</note> their duty is; 1. to honour and feare their Maſters; 2. to bee induſtrious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident for their good; 3. to be faithfull and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; 4. not to reply and multiply words.</p>
               <p>THis of the priuate iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice required in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, between the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and the Wife, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Children, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Seruants: The other is Publike in a Common-weale, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the duty of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Subiects, of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, Great and Smal.</p>
               <p>The duety of a Prince is already ſufficiently
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:19305:83"/> handled in the tract of politick Prudence, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his office both Prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paratiue and Actiue.<note place="margin">The duty of ſubiects.</note> The duty of Subiects conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth principally in three points, 1. to honour their Prince as Gods vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; 2. to obey his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to go to the wars to pay tributes and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts, and to conforme themſelues to all things that are iuſtly required by the lawes &amp; cuſtomes; 3. to pray for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of his perſon, his proſperity and happines.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The duty of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</note>The duety of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates followeth, in whom is required both honeſty, to keepe them from auarice, bribes, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:19305:83"/> reſpect of perſons, and courage to withſtand the commands of great men, the entreaties of friends, and the teares of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed: Their duety re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth the Prince and priuate men: their duty towards the Prince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in obeying his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts and commands, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther readily, ſlowly, or not at all. In thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that are iuſt and indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in themſelues, or thoſe that giue to the Magiſtrate acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and allowance with a warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table clauſe, there the Magiſtrate is to obey readily. In thoſe that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a clauſe derogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, where the Prince by
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:19305:84"/> his authority doth dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the law, there hee muſt alſo obey, but not ſo readily. In thoſe that haue no derogatory clauſe, but are wholly preiudiciall to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, hee ought to reſiſt once or twice, and not obey before the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or third command. But in thoſe that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Lawes of God and nature, he muſt not obey at all, but rather leaue his office, then ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke his conſcience.</p>
               <p>The duety of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> towards priuate men is this; to be alwaies at hand, to be of eaſie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, to heare al indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently as well poore as
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:19305:84"/> rich, and to be impartiall in the execution of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
               <p>The duty of great and ſmall,<note place="margin">The duty of the great</note> reſpecteth firſt the Great or Superiours, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the ſmall or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. The duty of the great is to ſpend their bloud and ability for the defence of Piety, Iuſtice, the Prince, the State, and Weale-publike, and to protect the poor and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed againſt the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the wicked, for this maketh them both beloued and adored.</p>
               <p>The duty of inferiors conſiſteth in this;<note place="margin">The duty of the ſmall</note> firſt to reuerence their ſuperiors, both ceremonially in outward ſhew (which is
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:19305:85"/> done as well to the bad as the good) and inwardly in loue and affection; and ſo they ought to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence only them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue well of the comon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: ſecondly, it is the duty, or rather the wiſdome of Inferiours to inſinuate by honeſt meanes into the fauour of great men, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, ſaith well, <hi>A friend in Court is worth a penny in purſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THe two laſt vertues whereby wee muſt guide our ſelues are For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and Temperance, theſe haue reſpect to the Accidents, Fortitude to
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:19305:85"/> the euill accidents of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, gouerning the iraſcible part of our ſoule, and Temperance to the ſeeming good of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ruling the concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible part.</p>
               <p>Fortitude is not (as ſome ſuppoſe) a loue of dangers,<note place="margin">Fortitude deſcribed.</note> or a deſire of dreadfull things (for this is temerity) neither doth it conſiſt in the bigneſſe of lookes or words, nor in Art and cunning, nor the ſtrength of the limbs (for ſo a ſwaggering Braggadochio, a Fencer, a horſe might be valiant) but in the reſolute cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the heart &amp; will, preſuppoſing the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all difficulties
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:19305:86"/> and dangers, as well mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary as other, and as wel the danger of the action and the diſcretion of the execution as the iuſtice of the cauſe. So that Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is a ſtrong reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the minde againſt all dolorous, difficult, and dangerous accidents whatſoeuer, grounded vpon the honeſty and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fortitude in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward euils</note>Now the ill accidents about which Fortitude is buſied, are eyther Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, which are aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, afflictions, iniuries, or internall, which are Paſſions. The externa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l or outward euils muſt be conſidered in their cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in their effects, and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:19305:86"/> diſtinctly in themſelues. The cauſes of them are eyther the iuſtice and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God, or the act of an other: Thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed immediately from the hand of God are commonly generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning many at the ſame inſtant, as peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, famine, tyranny, and the like; theſe are the yron ſcourges of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, therefore I omit them as comming from a ſupernaturall cauſe; But the beſt aduiſe in theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils is to turne to God by ſpeedy and harty repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and to ceaſe our wickedneſſe, that he may ceaſe his plagues. Thoſe euils that proceede from
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:19305:87"/> from the Act of an other are eyther ſuch as croſſe a mans affaires, or wrong his Perſon, eyther in word or deede. And the beſt aduice in this point is to reſpect firſt our ſelues, to carry ourſelues honeſtly, wiſely, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſion, that we giue an other no aduantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs; Secondly, the perſon that offends vs; and then (if it be a foole) it's wiſdome not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with him, but to leaue him to his folly; if it be a man of diſcretion, wee muſt conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee doth it out of malice or ignorance, and vſe him accordingly.</p>
               <p>Secondly, wee muſt
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:19305:87"/> conſider theſe outward euils in their effects, which are eyther gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or particular: their generall effects are for the publike good, as peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and famine are like a purge or a bloud letting in a corrupted body for the preſeruation of the whole; Their particular effects are diuers accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diuerſity of ſpirits vpon whom they fall: to the good they are a ſchoole of inſtruction; to the penitent a fatherly rodde, a bridle to keepe them from falling; to the reprobate a ſickle to cut them of, confuſion and perdition.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:19305:88"/> euils muſt be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered diſtinctly in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and ſo wee may note ſeuen kindes of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents which the world tearmeth principally e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, <hi>ſickneſſe, captiuity, banniſhment, pouerty, leſſe of friends, infamy, death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sickneſſe.</note>Sickneſſe is a priuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of health; and heerein the beſt remedy is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it patiently, 1. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is naturall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to our humane weakenes; 2. becauſe it is eyther ſhort if it bee vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and then it is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ended; or the paine but moderate if it bee long, and then it may be eaſily endured: 3. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is but the body
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:19305:88"/> that ſuffereth.</p>
               <p>Captiuity:<note place="margin">Captiuitie.</note> impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a priuation of li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berty, and heerein a man muſt likewiſe remembe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that it is but the body, the clogge and priſon of the ſoule that is impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the ſpirit remaining alwaies free and at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
               <p>Baniſhment or exile is a priuation of home-dwelling,<note place="margin">Baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> this a man may eaſily indure if hee conſider firſt that it is but a change of the place, <hi>et omne ſolum ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enti patria, euery place to a wiſe man is his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try;</hi> Secondly, that in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile a man leaues behinde him but the goods of
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:19305:89"/> fortune, not thoſe of the minde nor body: now a wiſe man carrieth all his goods with him, his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, honeſty, wiſedome, ſufficiency; theſe are properly a mans owne, from which he cannot be baniſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pouertie.</note>Pouerty is the want of meanes or maintenance; now there is a twofold want, the one of things neceſſary for nature, which befalleth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y few (for nature is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tent with a little) the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of ſuperfluities, for p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpe, pleaſure, delicacy; And in this want of pouerty, the beſt way is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with that which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity conſtraineth, <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benter
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:19305:89"/> velle quod ipſa cogit;</hi> and this a man may the better doe if he conſider firſt that hee came poore into the world (&amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. it is iniuſtice to grudge if hee depart ſo) ſecondly that pouerty is a ſecure eſtate, being free from the affaires, cares, incumbrances that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company riches.</p>
               <p>Infamy is the impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a mans honour,<note place="margin">Infamie.</note> worth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good name; and in this caſe it is beſt to conte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne the bad cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe enuy neuer ſpeakes well, and becauſe it is the companion of vertue.</p>
               <p>Loſſe of friends is a<note place="margin">Loſſe of friends.</note> priuation of the ſociety
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:19305:90"/> of Parents, wife, children or any that are neere and deere vnto vs. And in this caſe it behooues vs not to grieue exceſſiuely for the loſſe of any, firſt becauſe our plaints, our greefe, our teares are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectuall; ſecondly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we may gaine new friends by our honeſty and vertue: for hee that hath theſe, neuer wants friends.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Death.</note>Death is nothing but a priuation of life, whereof I haue ſpoken ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the frſt fruite of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fortitude in inward euils.</note>THis of outward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils: the other about which Fortitude is buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:19305:90"/> are inward euils ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the former; theſe are paſſions; <hi>feare, griefe, effeminate pitty, cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, enuy, reuenge, iealouſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt Feare the beſt remedies are theſe: firſt,<note place="margin">Againſt feare.</note> not to looke for the euil, nor to looke for it before it come becauſe it is but a caſuall accident, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vncertaine to come, or not to come vpon vs: ſecondly, to arme our ſelues to endure it ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if it come: and the better to doe this, a man muſt often giue vnto himſelfe the falſe allarum of a worſe ſuppoſed dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and thinke how hee could beare it, and how others haue borne more
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:19305:91"/> difficult and grieuous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt Griefe.</note>Againſt Griefe we muſt practiſe this, firſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the occaſion of it as a thing vnworthy to moleſt vs, ſecondly <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducere animum, to leade the minde out of the way,</hi> &amp; to diuert our thoughts from the cauſe of our griefe to ſome other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt Pittie.</note>Againſt Pittie or effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate compaſſion wee muſt learne to reſpect both the perſon and the cauſe that ſhould moue vs to pittie; ſecondly (if there bee neede) to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour him, but not to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with him, not to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues with the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:19305:91"/> care, the griefe, the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of another.</p>
               <p>Againſt Choler the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies are three;<note place="margin">Againſt Choler.</note> firſt to ſhunne the cauſes and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions thereof, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally theſe, tenderneſſe and delicateneſſe, curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, lightneſſe of beleefe, and a conceit of being ſlighted, contemned, or abuſed by another: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly to employ the meanes againſt the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of choler when it is offered; that is, to keepe our bodies in a cold tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, our ſelues ſilent and ſolitarie, and to vſe delay in beleeuing, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in reſoluing: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider the grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of mildneſſe and
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:19305:92"/> clemencie in others, and the hatefull inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the actions of them that are in choler.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt Hatred &amp; Enuie.</note>Againſt Hatred and Enuie (for theſe are of affinitie) we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well what it is that we hate or enuie in another, and learne to turne our hate into pittie, our enuy into reioycing; becauſe what wee hate in another we would be ſorry for in our ſelues, and what wee enuie in other, in our ſelues we would willingly embrace.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt Reuenge</note>Againſt Reuenge there are two remedies, the firſt is to haue recourſe vnto Clemencie to learne how to pardon, the ſecond is
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:19305:92"/> a hardy and couragious inſenſibilitie of ſuffering wrongs; which wee may ſhew either by doing good to the offender, or by ſcorning him and the offence as vnworthy to vrge vs to impatience, to reuenge.</p>
               <p>Againſt Iealouſie that proceeds from a mans wife the beſt remedies are theſe,<note place="margin">Againſt Iealouſie.</note> firſt for a man to be honeſt himſelfe, leſt he giue his wife a iuſt cauſe to requite him; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly not to be diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of her, vnleſſe hee know her diſloyall; thirdly (if he know it) to ſeeme to the world to take no notice of it, but to endure it patiently, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:19305:93"/> it is a common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, and his wifes fault, not his owne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce deſcribed.</note>THe laſt virtue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee muſt guide our ſelues is. Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which is a diſcreet moderation and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our ſelues in things that pleaſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: this virtue teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how to carry our ſelues well in <hi>proſperitie, pleaſure, eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, apparell, carnall copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, glory, ſpeech.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rules in proſperitie and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note>Of Proſperitie and Pleaſure I haue already ſpoken in the ſecond and third offices of wiſdome: all that I here deſire to
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:19305:93"/> inculcate is this; In pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie not to forget our ſelues, not to bee puffed vp, not to preſume; and concerning pleaſure, to vſe it like phyſicke, and to take it as men doe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, with the tip of the finger, not with a full hand; that is, not immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, not enthralling our ſelues to our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, not making of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure an occupation, not of ſport and recreation a toile or neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>In eating and drinking the aduiſements are theſe,<note place="margin">Eating &amp; drinking.</note> firſt to vſe no curious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, but mirth at meales in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtead of delicates and iuncats, <hi>ſine arte menſa, &amp; plus ſalis quàm ſumptus;</hi>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:19305:94"/> ſecondly to eat &amp; drinke moderately, not to bee ſuffocated, ſtuffed, nor filled with meats and drinkes; becauſe nature is ſufficed with a little, becauſe a full panch makes a man vnapt for any good worke, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the exceſſe in eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the latter) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds the memorie, duls the vnderſtanding, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers the body, and is the capitall cauſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Apparell.</note>Concerning apparell, it behoues vs to vſe it as a couering for our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and a ſhelter againſt the rigour of the weather, not for pride,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:19305:94"/> and in a word <hi>nec faciles &amp; vſitatas negligere mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditias, nec appetere delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas;</hi> we muſt neither neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect vſuall and frugall neatneſſe, nor follow the pompe, delicacie, curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſitie, nor the fantaſticall extrauagancie of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion.</p>
               <p>In Carnall pleaſure or copulation (which is a thing moſt naturall,<note place="margin">Carnall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation.</note> and therefore hard to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained) the beſt aduiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are theſe, firſt to keepe our ſelues from the alluring baits of beautie, for this is a good helpe both to a virgin and a coniugall continencie; ſecondly to attaine this pleaſure by good and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:19305:95"/> honeſt meanes; thirdly to vſe it moderately and chaſtely, for a man may commit adulterie with his wife.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Glory and ambition.</note>Concerning Glory or Ambition (which is <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car virtutis, the pricke and ſpurre of virtue</hi>) the beſt precept is this; To vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take no good, beautifull, or honourable attempt, ſo much for glory as for the loue of virtue; for our owne conſcience is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter witneſſe of our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then the opinion of the people; and virtue in it ſelfe is worthy and rich enough, and brings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſufficient with it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Speech.</note>Laſt of all, in our
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:19305:95"/> ſpeech it will be expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to obſerue theſe rules; firſt to ſpeake lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and that truly, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, and without affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation and paſſion; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly to ſpeake ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, not of friuolous things, not of things la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciuious, not of our owne actions; thirdly to ſpeake plauſibly, without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, without detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without mockerie; fourthly to haue the tongue in the heart, not the heart in the tongue.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The heart and tong of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhew the proofe.</l>
                  <l>Rule theſe two well, &amp; thou art wiſe enough.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19305:96"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19305:96"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt part of this Booke, teaching the knowledge of our ſelues.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F Wiſedome in generall, <hi>P. 1</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of humane Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>4</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of man <hi>2.</hi> waies conſidered, naturally &amp; morally, <hi>6</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19305:97"/>
                  <item>The firſt naturall conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of man by the compoſition of his parts, <hi>7</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the braine, which here is onely handled, and the other parts omitted, <hi>8</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the three faculties of the humane ſoule, <hi>9</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the vegetatiue facultie, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the ſenſitiue, <hi>10</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the intellectiue and the three faculties thereof, <hi>11</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the imagination, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the vnderſtanding, <hi>12</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the memory, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the Paſſions, <hi>ibid</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Loue in generall, <hi>15</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Ambition, <hi>16</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Couetouſneſſe, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Concupiſcence, <hi>17</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19305:97"/>
                  <item>Of Ioy, <hi>18</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Deſire, <hi>19</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Hope, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Deſpaire, <hi>20</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Hate, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Feare, <hi>21</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Griefe, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pittie, <hi>22</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Choler, <hi>23</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Enuy, <hi>24</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Iealouſie, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Reuenge, <hi>25</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Crueltie, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The ſecond naturall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of man by his difference from other creatures, <hi>26</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The third by his life, <hi>28</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The firſt Morall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man by his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and conditions <hi>30</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Vanitie, <hi>31</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19305:98"/>
                  <item>Weakneſſe, <hi>33</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Inconſtancie, <hi>35</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Miſerie, <hi>36</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Preſumption, <hi>37</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The ſecond Morall conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of man by the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of one man from another, <hi>40</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Firſt in reſpect of the Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate where they liue, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly in reſpect of their capacitie and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>42</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly in reſpect of ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie and inferioritie, <hi>43</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fourthly in reſpect of the diuerſitie of their profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and kinde of life, <hi>45</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fiftly in reſpect of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours and disfauours of nature and fortune, <hi>47</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:19305:98"/>
               <head>The ſecond part of this Booke, ſhewing the generall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>THe Preparatiues vnto Wiſdome, <hi>52</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The foundations of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>54</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The offices of Wiſdome, <hi>57</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The fruits of Wiſdome, <hi>75</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third part of this Booke, ſhewing the particular inſtructions of Wiſdome by the rule of the foure morall virtues.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>OF Prudence in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, <hi>81</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19305:99"/>
                  <item>Of Politike Prudence, <hi>82</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Preparatiue office of a Prince, <hi>83</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Actiue office of a Prince, <hi>97</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Prudence required in difficult affaires and ill accidents both publik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and priuate, <hi>11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of euill accidents to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of euill accidents preſent, <hi>113</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Doubtfull affaires, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dangerous affaires, <hi>114</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Coniuration, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Treaſon, <hi>115</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Popular commotions, <hi>116</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sudden tumults, <hi>117</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Faction and confederacy. <hi>117</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sedition, <hi>118</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Rebellion. <hi>120</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19305:99"/>
                  <item>Ciuill warre. ibid.</item>
                  <item>How particular perſons ſhould carry themſelues in theſe publike diuiſions, <hi>122</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of priuate troubles and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions. <hi>123</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Of Iuſtice the ſecond Vertue.</head>
                  <item>Of the iuſtice and duety of man towards himſelfe, <hi>124</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the iuſtice and duety of man towards man. <hi>127</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The common dueties of all towards all. ib.</item>
                  <item>Of Amity and friendſhip, <hi>128</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Faith and fidelity. <hi>132</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of verity and free admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>133</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19305:100"/>
                  <item>Of benefits and thanke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The ſpeciall dueti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quired of certaine by ſpeciall obl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation.</head>
                  <item>The duties of marrie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of Houſhold Husba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>The duety of parents a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> children, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>The duty of Maſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Seruants. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 155</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The duty of Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Subiects. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>The duety of Magiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>The duty of great &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19305:100"/>
                  <head>Fortitude the third Vertue.</head>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de in outward euils, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>162</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eneſſe. <hi>166</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiuity. <hi>167</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhment. ibid.</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouerty. <hi>168</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he loſſe of friends. <hi>169</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amy. ibid.</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath. <hi>170</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itude in inward euills. ibid.</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inſt feare. <hi>171</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>172</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. ibid.</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. <hi>173</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed. <hi>174</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y. ibid.</item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enge. ibid.</item>
                  <item>Iealouſie. <hi>175</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19305:101"/>
                  <head>Of Temperance the fourth Vertue.</head>
                  <item>Of proſperity. <hi>176</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of pleaſure. ibid.</item>
                  <item>Of eating and drinking. <hi>177</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of apparell. <hi>178</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of carnall pleaſure. <hi>179</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of glory and ambition. <hi>180</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of ſpeech. ibid.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis tabulae.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19305:101"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
